<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Ansvver to a libell intituled, A coole conference betweene the cleered Reformation and the apologeticall narration; brought together by a wel-willer to both; wherein are cleerely refuted what ever he bringeth against the Reformation cleared, most humbly submitted to the judgement of the honourable Houses of Parliament, the most learned and reverend divines of the assembly, and all the reformed churches. By Adam Steuart.</title>
            <author>Steuart, Adam.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93883</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E43_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11438</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859030</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859030</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111091</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93883)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111091)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E43[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Ansvver to a libell intituled, A coole conference betweene the cleered Reformation and the apologeticall narration; brought together by a wel-willer to both; wherein are cleerely refuted what ever he bringeth against the Reformation cleared, most humbly submitted to the judgement of the honourable Houses of Parliament, the most learned and reverend divines of the assembly, and all the reformed churches. By Adam Steuart.</title>
                  <author>Steuart, Adam.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reformation of church-government in Scotland cleered from some mistakes was written by Alexander Henderson in defense of the Scottish Commissioners.  The Apologeticall narration was written by Thomas Goodwin and other Independents.  The Coole conference was anonymous.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Apr: 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henderson, Alexander, 1583?-1646. --  Reformation of church-government in Scotland cleered from some mistakes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologeticall narration, humbly submitted to the honourable Houses of Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Coole conference between the cleared reformation and the apologeticall narration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111091:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111091:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSVVER TO A LIBELL INTITULED, A COOLE CONFERENCE Between the cleered <hi>REFORMATION</hi> AND THE APOLOGETICALL NARRATION, Brought together by a Wel-willer to both; Wherein are cleerely refuted what ever he bringeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Reformation cleared, moſt humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the judgement of the Honourable Houſes of Parliament, the moſt Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Divines of the Aſſembly, and all the Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>By ADAM STEVART.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amb. lib. 5.</hi> de Fide.</bibl>
               <p>Si taceamus conſentire videbimur; ſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendamus verendum ne carnales judicemur.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111091:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111091:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous</hi> Reader; <hi>I pray thee excuſe ſome of the moſt materiall faults, fallen out, partly by my abſence, partly by an accident that befell the Copy, and to correct them as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PAge 3. line 8. read neither ſhould he have feared a ſuppreſſion of his book, p. 10. l. 11. <hi>dele</hi> all that paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis, ibid. p. l. 20. <hi>dele</hi> becauſe, p. 11. l. 9. read and thoſe who intereſſe. p. 16. l. 24. for but ſo, r. and ſo, p. 19. l. 26. r. for it was, 1. it was, p. 22. <hi>d.</hi> men, p. 25. l. 3. r. Anſw. 1. ib. p. l. 5. for how, r. 2. How, ibid. p. l. 8. after the word Communion adde all that followeth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Either this Wel-willer pretendeth to play the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſt or the Divine: If the Naturaliſt, he knoweth not well the nature of the Northerly winde, for ordinarily it bringeth not blacke, but faire weather, and ſcattereth the clouds, as he might learne of all Naturaliſts, <hi>ab Aqualone aurum,</hi> from the North commeth gold, <hi>i.e.</hi> golden or fair weather, <hi>Iob</hi> 37.22. The North winde driveth away rain, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.23. If he play the Divine, and allude to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb facs="tcp:111091:3"/>I muſt ſay to him as Chriſt ſaid to the Jewes, Ye erre, not underſtanding the Scriptures; for there it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth either the Spirit of Chriſt, as in <hi>Salomons</hi> Song. And then he muſt pray with the Church, A wake O North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winde, and come thou South, blow upon my garden that the ſpices thereof may flow out, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16. Or Gods people who were Northerne in reſpect of the Philiſtins, who were their enemies; ſo we muſt be Gods people, and the Independenters (whom this Wel-willer oppoſeth to the North) their enemies; or the Babylonians who were ſeptentrionall, or North-ward, in reſpect of Gods people, <hi>Eſay</hi> 41.25. and ſo he eſteemeth us to be Gods enemies; if ſo, how hold they us for one of the moſt pure Churches? but what ever it ſignifie, it can never ſignifie the Church of Scotland, but in a very good ſenſe. Pag. 27. <hi>d.</hi> us, p. 28. for Heb. <hi>panegr.</hi> r. as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23. l. <hi>ult.</hi> for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 29. l. 8. for vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit r. ye vomit, p. 29. l. 30. <hi>d.</hi> of my ſelfe, p. 43. l. 27. for two read five, p. 35. l. 29. after the word narration, adde all this that followeth.</p>
            <p>Onely I pray the Reader to conſider theſe mens craft in going about to ſow the ſeeds of diviſion betwixt the civill Magiſtrat &amp; the orthodox Churches, in making the world to beleeve that they grant him more then the maximes of Presbyteriall Government will ſuffer them to do. For, 1. They tell not wherein: 2. Whether this power be Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall or Civill, as for the Eccleſiaſticall they cannot give it: 1. It being onely a Miniſteriall power to ſerve, &amp; not Magiſteriall to dominiere with, or to be given away by proxy, to whom they pleaſe. 2. If they give the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat any power, what can it be? is it to preach, to teach, the power of the Keies to Excommunicate, or to attend
<pb facs="tcp:111091:3"/>upon the ſick and poore people? and as for the civill it is not theirs, but His Majeſties and the Magiſtrates, as is the conſtant tenet of all the Orthodox Churches, who hold the Civill power incompatible with that of a Paſtour or Doctor of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If they grant the Magiſtrate more power then our Churches, how is it that they acknowledge the Kings Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in New-England for nothing elſe but in matters of State or Civill Government, and Gods word onely in Church Government?</p>
            <p n="4">4. He and they alſo hold the ſame rule in Old-England, and therefore I pray all men only to conſider if this be not rather a gulling of the Civill Magiſtrate, then a proof of what they ſay.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I wiſh him to anſwer whether New-England depend of Old-England, and whether they thinke the King and Parliament have power to change Religion and Church Government there?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether they both have power to do the ſame here againſt Gods word?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Whether the Parliament have done well or not in calling of this Aſſembly of Divines, to judge of matters of Religion? As for us, the conſtant opinion of all our Churches is, that all Civill power belongeth onely to the Civill Magiſtrate, and none at all to the Church. 2. That the Civill Magiſtrate hath an extrinſecall executive power about Religion to maintaine and reforme it, in caſe of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and that according to the preſidents in Scripture; Neither did ever any good Chriſtian Prince aſſume any more to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Neither doth it any way leſſen his power, that it is only extrinſecall; for to be intrinſecall or extrinſecall ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:111091:4"/>not any quantity of greater or leſſer power, but onely the manner thereof; for an extrinſecall power and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, may be greater then an intrinſecall as appeareth in that of the efficient and Materiall cauſe, for the firſt is only active, and yet extrinſecall; but the ſecond meerely paſſive without any action or efficacy at all and yet intrinſecall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>PErlegi tractatum hunc, in quo nihil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio quo minus cum utilitate publicâ imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>IA. CRANFORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111091:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore I beginne the Refutation of this Pamphlet, it ſhall not be amiſſe, that I apologize for my ſelfe, for refuting a Book already ſufficiently refuted of it ſelfe, and by that very ſame Booke, whereof it intendeth the refutation: I will therefore here declare unto the Chriſtian Reader how I came to undertake it; how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing I was to doe it; upon what reaſons I was moved thereunto. The truth therefore is thus: That ſome daies after the publication of this booke, I hapned to fall in company with ſome men of quality that were reading of it, and after the peruſall thereof, it was the joint wiſh of them all that ſome anſwer were drawne up unto it. A few dayes after that, I chanced to re-encounter with ſome of the ſame company, and ſome others very well affected to Reformation, who after ſundry diſcourſes fell upon the ſame Theme againe, ſome of them ſaying that it would doe well that the Commiſſioners of the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land would anſwer it. Where ſome of them deſiring me to deliver my opinion, I replyed ſeverall times (as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on required) in ſubſtance that which followeth; That it might ſeeme ſtrange to others if men of ſuch gravity and learning, and much more of ſo eminent place and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111091:5"/>repreſenting the whole Nationall Church of the Kingdome of Scotland, ſhould ſtoop to anſwer every idle Anonymus Pamphleter, peradventure ſome Anabaptiſt, peradventure ſome Don<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a <hi>Catherina</hi> (it may be of purpoſe) put upon the Stage, to make them ridiculous, if they ſhould acknowledge ſuch inconſiderable perſons as a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble party. Beſides this I told them, that I thought the Author of the Booke was a man very ill-bred, and impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and that for many reaſons; and among the reſt, Firſt, becauſe he being (as it ſeemeth) but a private man, he will needs be begging of a quarrell with the Scotch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, who never offended him, nor (for any thing that appeareth) knew not whether hee was <hi>inverum natura,</hi> or not. Secondly, and if he pretend that they offended ſome of his Sect, <hi>viz.</hi> the five Authors of the Apologeticall Narration; then ſeemes he yet unwiſer then I tooke him to be, eſteeming ſo highly of himſelfe, as if he were abler to anſwer for them, then they for themſelves: ſo judge not wiſe men, much leſſe this wiſe Parliament, for then haply it had made choice of him to have beene a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Aſſembly, which yet it did not. Thirdly, they are of age, very able men according to all wiſe mens judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore it ſeemeth more fit that they anſwer for themſelves; and ſo much rather, becauſe neither they depend of him, nor he of them, nor any of them one from another; or all, or any of them, from any ſuperiour Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall power; but every one of them ſtandeth for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. And finally, if they had offended thoſe five vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſons, or their Sect, in apologizing for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of all the Orthodox Churches, and namely that of Scotland, whereof they be Commiſſioners, (howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver no offence appeareth) 1. yet offended they them not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111091:5"/>in particular: 2. Neither tooke they them directly for parties: 3. Or their Apologeticall Narration formally to refute, no more then they five tooke the foure Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners for their formall party, or the Diſcipline of the Orthodox Churches, or that of Scotland formally to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute. If this Anonymus Divine had imitated the prudence of either of them, hee would have appeared wiſer then now he doth; neither ſhould his Booke needed to have beene ſuppreſſed (as it is) in nature of an infamous Libell. Hereupon I was deſired to ſet upon the worke my ſelfe: Whereunto I anſwered, that hardly could I doe it, not knowing who was the Author of it, or of what Sect or Sex he might be. They taking this my anſwer for a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, which I gave them in good earneſt, replyed, That it could not be a woman, fince the Independents permit not them to write Bookes: but this ſatisfied not at all: for howſoever the Quinqu' Eccleſian Miniſters admit them not to judge of controverſies in Doctrine, or in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall cenſures, yet is it but a particular opinion of thoſe five, and of ſome others; and however they admit them not to ſuch acts, yet may it be doubted whether they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them not to write Bookes of Divinity. Afterwards they would willingly have perſwaded mee that it was no Anabaptiſt, ſince he was an Independent, and diſclaimed them, and ſpoke contemptuouſly of them: But that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no more ſatisfactory then the reſt: 1. For howſoever all Independenters be not Anabaptiſts, yet all Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, all Sectaries, and Heretickes at this preſent about London, pretend to bee <hi>Independents.</hi> 2. That the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts here in London for the moſt part agree with them in all things, ſave onely in delaying of Baptiſme till the time that the parties to be baptized be of age ſufficient to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111091:6"/>give an account of their faith; and in re-baptizing ſuch as are baptized in all other Churches, ſave thoſe of their owne Sect, as I have heard of themſelves. 3. Sundry of the Independents alſo hold them for very good men, as they declare to the people in their Sermons, what ever they write to the contrary. 4. Many of them alſo hold the Anabaptiſt errour very tolerable, which is (it may be) the cauſe that ſo many daily fall away from Independen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to Anabaptiſme; and that not without juſt cauſe: for if the Independents ſtand to their owne principles, and hold no men to bee Members of Chriſts Church, or viſible Chriſtians, till they be able to give <hi>account</hi> of their <hi>faith,</hi> and of the <hi>motions of grace</hi> that they feele within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, what need they to Chriſten thoſe that are not vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Chriſtians? Wherefore delay they not Baptiſme as the Anabaptiſts? and that ſo much the more, ſince they refuſe it to ſome of the children of thoſe of their owne Sect. However they eſteeme their parents to bee very godly, and that onely becauſe they were not churched, or received into Church Covenant with them before their death. Some other reaſons were alledged, which here I omit. To bee ſhort, I was entreated againe to anſwer the Booke, which I promiſed to doe, if the Author could bee diſcovered; whereupon they did what they could, ſo did I alſo, but could not certainly diſcover him. In fine, I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered my ſelfe for ſome particular reaſons to be perſwaded by them. Onely before I enter the liſts with him, ſince the Author will needs march under a veyle, and conceale himſelfe, I ſhall pray the Chriſtian Reader and him both to excuſe me, if without any reſpect to his perſon, I refute his Booke as it deſerveth.</p>
            <p>Whatever he be, for feare leſt good men bee deceived
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111091:6"/>under pretext of his pretended piety, with ſo many of his <hi>Abs,</hi> and <hi>deare Brethren,</hi> I pray them to obſerve in him, or at leaſt in his Booke, his great weakneſſe, yea (if I may by his permiſſion ſay it) his great wickedneſſe in theſe points following. 1. He would make the world beleeve, that the Scots Commiſſioners acknowledge ſome defects and errors in their Diſcipline, <hi>p.</hi> 1. which againſt the knowne light of their conſcience they will not reforme. 2. Hee falſifieth the Covenant, in adding ſome words to it, which corrupt the ſenſe, <hi>p.</hi> 1.3. And that to extenuate his perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie inferres, cleering and expreſſing thoſe equivocations and mentall reſervations which before he concealed, <hi>p.</hi> 4. he denieth that the Synod gave any thankes to the Scots Commiſſioners for their Reply to the Apologetical Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or rather for the cleared Reformation, <hi>p.</hi> 3. which I ſubmit to the Synods judgement, whether there be not an Act of theirs to the contrary of what he ſaith in this point. He will perſwade the Reader, that the Synod only voyced them thanks for a two penny Booke which they gave them, as if that grave Aſſembly had nothing elſe to doe.</p>
            <p>I might note many more untruths; if he had had any prudence he might have learned the contrary either in the City, or at Weſtminſter Hal: but the Scripture muſt be true, <hi>The labour of the fooliſh wearieth every one of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knoweth not how to goe to the City.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>The wicked is ſnared by the tranſgreſsion of his mouth.</hi> And this I pray the Reader to examine, and not to ſuffer himſelfe to be miſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by any prejudicate opinion of his apparent pietie, his ſmooth ſtyle with his <hi>ſweet Brethren,</hi> but to examine all things, and to retaine what is good, and to conſider, that a man ſo bold and adventrous, as to propound in face of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111091:7"/>this moſt honourable and wiſe Parliament, the venerable Aſſembly of ſo godly and learned Divines, and of all the world, ſo many, ſo palpable untruths, muſt needs be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paſſionate for thoſe opinions, which with ſo blinde a zeale, and ſo little care of his credit hee maintaineth here, and may be no leſſe paſſionate in other things then in this. As for the reaſons and motives inducing me to refute this Libell, they were not any ſtuffe the Booke contained, or the leaſt feare I had that it could worke upon any rationall man; nor ſet I upon it with purpoſe to offend any man, no not the five Independent Members of the Synod; yea, nor ſo much as the Author of this Libell, (who has ſo highly offended all the beſt Reformed Churches) for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any one of them offended me; neither is it their Act, neither beleeve I that they had any hand in it; or if they had any, they avow it not. And as for the Author, I can not offend him wittingly, ſince I know him not, and this I hope would excuſe very much the offence, if any ſhould be: nor indeed ought hee to take offence at this Anſwer, ſince he dare not owne the Booke. Now if he be either a wiſe man, or any wayes gracious, I ſuppoſe hee ought rather to thanke mee for ſuch an ingenuous reproving of his wicked calumnies againſt the whole body of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches; for, <hi>A reproofe</hi> (ſaith the Wiſeman) <hi>entreth more into a wiſe man, then an hundred ſtripes into a foole.</hi> Beſides, as I conceive, it is an act of love: for as a Father ſaith,<note place="margin">Auſt. Epiſt. ad Mate.</note> 
               <hi>Magis amat objurgator ſanans, quam adulator diſsimulans.</hi> Neither can ſuch indignities well bee endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by any man, that knoweth how handſomly to caſt them off, eſpecially when they are publiſhed in Print, and that becauſe of the imminent danger thereby of infecting the weaker ſort of people, not onely that now are, but alſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111091:7"/>of the poſterity to come. For, as ſaith the Roman Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher: <hi>Vitia tranſmittis ad poſteres,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. de Morib.</note> 
               <hi>qui praſentibus culpis parcit.</hi> But if he ſhould be ſo fond as to thinke that he has done well in what he has done, yet ſhall this Anſwer have ſome effect upon him: for as <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith well,<note place="margin">Greg in Paſt.</note> 
               <hi>Protervos tunc melius corrigimus, cum aequae bene egiſſe credunt, male acta monſtramus, ut unde adepta gloria creditur, inde utilis confeſsio ſequatur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for me I can truly ſay, my principall aime and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive was Gods honour, the vindication of the Proteſtant Churches, and eſpecially that of Scotland from this mans vilde aſperſions, and to give contentment to good people, who I am afraid may have beeno deceived with the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious pretext of this mans piety; and particularly, that I might comply with the deſires of thoſe my worthy friends that moved me hereunto. And ſo come I to the Title of the Booke, which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A coole Conference betweene the cleered Reformation and the Apologeticall Narration, braught together by a well willer to both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here it is to be obſerved, 1. That this Booke carrieth with it no Approbation by thoſe who are ordained by the Parliament to licence the printing of any Bookes: From whence it may be inferred, that in ſo contemning their Lawes and Ordinances, and afterwards in maintaining, that Independents (of whom hee pretendeth to bee one) give more to the Civill Magiſtrate, then the principles of Presbyterian Government permit them to doe; that this is done, and that ſaid in deriſion of them both, and by a man no wiſe minded to practiſe what hee ſaith or profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111091:8"/>by ſome <hi>Noſtro damus</hi> of whom it is ſaid,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Noſtro damus cum verba damus quia fallere noſtrum;</l>
               <l>Et cum verba damus, nil niſi noſtr a damus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Or rather done as the Souldiers did to Chriſt, who bowed the knee to him, ſaying, <hi>Haile King of the Iewes,</hi> and mocked him, &amp; ſpit upon him. He giveth them much Paper-honour with much reall diſgrace, and will live as Independent upon all Civill as all Eccleſiaſticall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is to be obſerved, as I ſaid before, that the Author taketh no proper name to himſelfe, but onely is deſcribed by a common name, which is more ordinary among beaſts then men. For as mens individuall Natures and Perſons are ſignified by proper Names, ſo are all beaſts ordinarily repreſented by names common to the whole Species, if you except a few tame beaſts: ſo here there is no <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduum ſignatum</hi> for to owne this Pamphlet, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſome judicious men to thinke, that he found himſelfe conſcious of what I have ſaid, or am to ſay; and therefore went cunningly to worke in not owning it, for feare of ſome caſtigation in ſtead of confutation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That this Authors common Name here is a Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willer to both, whereupon at firſt, before that I had read over the Booke, I wondred much what ſort of creature this could bee, what <hi>Hybrida</hi> and <hi>Amphisbaena</hi> in matter of Religion, bred of ſo oppoſite Species, having its heads in ſo oppoſite parts, carried by ſo contrary motions, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo contrary ends, <hi>viz.</hi> of Dependency and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency. But afterwards in running it over I found no ſuch thing anſwerable to the Frontiſpiece, neither in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor in manner. For it ye conſider the firſt, it is nothing elſe but an intended juſtification (howſoever with little
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111091:8"/>ſucceſſe) of the Apologeticall Narration, and a ſenſleſſe arraignment of the Reformation cleared: If the ſecond likewiſe, his expreſſions, which bee evermore <hi>we, us, our,</hi> &amp;c. teſtifie moſt evidently, that hee is a formall partie. Truly hee willeth the Commiſſioners ſo little, and his Quinqu 'Eccleſian Miniſters ſo much good in this cauſe, that he would make the world beleeve that the one partie ſaith all, and the other nothing at all. But what ever good ye will them, pardon us if we give you no credit till they be brought together, and it bee ſeene what each of them can ſay for themſelves. In the meane time I pray the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to take notice how this man in the evry threſhold fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes us with ſo evident an argument of his weakneſſe, in that, intending a diſguiſement, he had no better contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, then by his owne penne ſo ſhamefully to bewray himſelfe. Alas poore man, that profeſſing here ſo much truth and honeſtie, thou ſhouldſt thus foully betray thy ſelfe to be neither true nor honeſt. He endeth his Booke in an extraordinary way, with an &amp;c. intimating ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Booke behinde, and afterward <hi>Finis,</hi> aſſuring us of nothing behinde; as if his onely aime were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelfe, and ſo to try our patience, and his owne parties credulity, how farre the contrary partie will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, or his owne admit ſuch palpable untruths, both in the beginning, and in the end of his Book. Eccleſiaſt. 10.32. <hi>The word of a foole will ſwallow himſelfe: The beginning of the words of his mouth is fooliſhneſſe, and the end of his talke is miſchievous madneſſe.</hi> O what a ſhame in this Prophet that profeſſeth ſuch pietie, that the lying ſpirit ſhould ſo prevaile in his mouth! 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22.22. If it pleaſe the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader to goe along with me in the Examen of it, he ſhall finde him no better in the midſt, ſo he ſhall have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111091:9"/>him (by Gods grace) compleatly like to himſelfe <hi>in Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio, Medio, &amp; Fine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Title or Inſcription of his Book is <hi>A coole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</hi> The Author might have ſaid, A very hot and coole Conference, for it is ſo hot for the one partie, that ye may eſteeme it a burning coale, or fire of zeale for it, howſoever without knowledge: <hi>igneus eſt illi vigor &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtris origo.</hi> But for the other it is ſo coole, yea ſo cold in its behalfe, that he may be judged to be <hi>ex frigidis &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leficiatis,</hi> or this his diſcourſe to be dropped from <hi>Diacal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, Driſwerus, Noſedropenſis,</hi> who wrote <hi>de frigidis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor is Nive; Glacie &amp; Grandine.</hi> Neither can it aſcend to the ſupreme Region of the Ayre, or produce any effect upon great ſpirits.</p>
            <q>Nec faciles motus mens generoſacapit.</q>
            <p>If it work at all, it muſt bee in the loweſt Region thereof, and upon very weake braines, who will not hearken unto the truth. But not to inſiſt upon the Title of the Booke, I come to the Booke it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt page, becauſe the Scotch Commiſſioners ſay, <hi>We are neither ſo ignorant, nor ſo arrogant, as to aſcribe to the Church of Scotland ſuch abſolute puruy and perfection, as hath not need, or cannot admit of further Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I am aſſured, that there is no man that profeſſes Chriſtianitie that can finde fault with this humble and moſt modeſt expreſſion; and yet this well-willing Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleter ſets himſelfe to jeere at it, as <hi>a golden peace ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſpeech, as if dropped from the mouth of ſome</hi> Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, <hi>or conceived by ſome</hi> Ireneus. But it is no new thing that men of <hi>golden,</hi> and <hi>peaceable ſpirits,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Ireneus,</hi> ſhould meet with enemies, ſuch as theirs were: for <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> had adverſaries who had <hi>ferreum os, aeneam
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111091:9"/>frontem, plumbeum cerebrum;</hi> and <hi>Ireneus</hi> had his, who were every whit as buſily <hi>cudere</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as he could be <hi>cudere</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon this he groundeth a <hi>latitude</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> as I beleeve, greater then that of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, to receive all ſorts of cleane and unclean beaſts: but we deſire to know of what <hi>latitude</hi> he would have it; if it ſhall receive Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Anabaptiſts, and the Independenters of New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, who intereſſe all the people, yea women too to judge in matters of Religion, and in all Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures whatſoever.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Under condition of his <hi>latitude</hi> of <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, or rather of the Regions of the world, he aſſureth us of their Good will acccording to the <hi>Covenant, wherein they ſweare to endeavour the preſervation of the reformed Religion in Scotland, in Doctrine Worſhip, Diſcipline and Government, againſt our common enemies; the Reformation of Religion in the Kingdomes of England and Ireland, in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, according to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt reformed Churches; And ſhall endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdomes to the neereſt conjunction and uniformity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Confeſsion of faith, and form of Church Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here we ſee no latitude nor condition.</p>
            <p>But the Pamphleter to ſhew his wit and skill, and how cunningly he can draw the guilt of perjury upon himſelfe, has recourſe to a <hi>Gloſſe</hi> of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and ſome mentall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, whereby he ſtrangely tortureth the Covenant againſt the Text. Hee telleth us that the Covenant onely ſaith, the <hi>Reformed Religion in Scotland, that is, or ſhall bee; and till further Reformation wee will preſerve it againſt our common enemy.</hi> But never a word in the Covenant <hi>of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111091:10"/>Reformation of the Religion in Scotland, that is or ſhall be; and till further Reformation.</hi> This is an <hi>addition</hi> to the Text, yea a meere falſification of the Covenant. The Covenant ſpeaketh onely of an endeavour of the reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in England and Ireland, according to the word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches, wherof it preſuppoſeth that of Scotland to be one, 1. ſince it ſweareth to preſerve it; Neither could the Covenanters ſweare to preſerve it, if they thought it to bee deformed, for that were to ſweare to maintaine deformity in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. 2. And this may further be confirmed, for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is <hi>finis intenti ſed non adepti;</hi> of a thing intended, that as yet is not exiſtent, but to exiſt; but preſervation is of a thing already exiſtent, and ſuppoſed to be. 3. Becauſe it is ſo expounded in the thankſgiving of the Aſſembly to the Scots Commiſſioners for their Booke. Neither for all this beleeve wee that the Reformed Churches, and namely that of Scotland cannot erre, as the Romaniſts at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute unto their Church: But the queſtion is only whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no they doe erre, and wherein? if in that, that they will not receive the Independent Anarchie, and Papalitie into every particular Congregation, in permitting their particular Conſiſtory compounded of one Miniſter, and two or three ruling Elders, to judge ſo many hundreds of perſons, who will not ſuffer themſelves to be judged by any, yea not by the whole Chriſtian world: If in this, or any other thing they erre, they profeſſe themſelves ready to bee informed, and afterwards reformed. But becauſe they are fallible, and may erre, to conclude therefore that in every thing wherein they differ from Independenters, Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, &amp;c. they doe erre, and ſo to quit their <hi>Religion,</hi> they are not ſuch fooles; for by the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111091:10"/>reaſon we might as well conclude our Brethren ſhould quit their <hi>Tenets,</hi> and come to us.</p>
            <p>P. 2. Apol. <hi>Ah deare Brethren:</hi> Here he calleth us deare, and ſweet Brethren: but this Doctor had need of a <hi>Doctor,</hi> for his palate is ſo feveriſh and vitiated, that he reliſhes bitterneſſe in the ſweet expreſſions of thoſe whom he calleth ſweet Brethren; and his conceptions are ſo far diſordered, that he applieth to the Apologiſts what the <hi>Reformation cleared</hi> ſaith of ignorant and ill-informed people onely; and doth not apply that, which juſtly he might have applied to them in the following words, <hi>viz.</hi> the miſrepreſentations and indirect aſperſions of others, <hi>who doe ſo commend,</hi> &amp;c. and this diſtinction appeareth cleerly by thoſe particles <hi>(miſtakings of ſome, and miſ-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This well-willer telleth us, that <hi>wiſe men are ſilently intentive, expecting diſputed poſitions from the Aſſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> And why not ye alſo, ſince in the laſt diſputed <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition</hi> ye caried away ſo great glory. If good <hi>Cato</hi> ſay true, <hi>Virtutem primam eſſe puta compeſcere linguam,</hi> truly ye had the chiefe of all vertues, and that in a moſt high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, yea in <hi>gradu heroico,</hi> for ye troubled the Aſſembly very little with any <hi>Reply</hi> to what they anſwered you. But will ye, our Well-willer, either give us, or let us give you ſome poſitions upon this Subject, that we may receive of you ſome edification in particular at leaſt, if we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have it in publick. Here I offer you a man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe whatſoever poſitions you pleaſe, in all points, wherein yee diſſent from all Proteſtant and Chriſtian Churches. And ſince you put us in minde of it, let me tell you, ſome have been very deſirous to have had ſome acceſſe to ſome of your Miniſters, to the end they might have received ſome edification of them, and have known
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111091:11"/>their opinions, but found them evermore inacceſſible; ſo deſirous were they, it ſhould ſeem, to hide their opinions. As for your <hi>Prodromus,</hi> which ye ſay <hi>hath not deſerved to be whipt, if the Parliament permit any of the Aſſembly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering one from another in opinion, to preſent their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with their reaſons unto the Houſes, you cannot judge it a crime, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is already anſwered by the Author of the Obſervations and Annotations upon the Apologeticall Narration. 2. This Propoſition is conditionall, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever hath the leaſt tincture in Logick, knoweth, that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionalis propoſitio nil ponit in re, niſi poſitâ conditione.</hi> 3. And if the Parliament permit it not in this your fooliſh faſhion, what will you ſay? 4. What if very wiſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men already ſay, that if in the Generall Councells every one that differed in opinion one from another, had written bookes one againſt another, they ſhould rather have been held for Councells of fooles then of wiſe men. 5. And if it be ſo, (as you ſay,) wherefore I pray ſhould not the Scotch Commiſſioners have written againſt your Apologeticall Narration; ſince they differed in opinion from the Apologiſts, and ſo much the rather, being that they were calumniated by them.</p>
            <p>He complaineth alſo of their bitterneſſe; And I on the other ſide wonder at their patience and meekneſſe, that they have ſo little gall againſt Innovators, calumniating the government of all Proteſtant, yea of all Chriſtian Churches, except their owne Conventicles, as <hi>deſtitute of the power of godlineſſe,</hi> and as Papiſts, and Lutherans, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faming them with nicknames, as <hi>Calvinians, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 3. He asks the Authors of the Reformation cleared, if they thinke that the Elders of the <hi>quinque Eccleſiae</hi> be dark?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111091:11"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who theſe Elders of the <hi>quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſiae</hi> can be, I know not: I have read in the Revelation of the Angels of 7 <hi>Eccleſiae;</hi> in the Councell of Trent, <hi>de Dudithio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopo Quinqu' Eccleſienſi,</hi> and of a Town in <hi>Hungaria</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Eccleſiae,</hi> at this preſent under <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and by the Turks named <hi>Porſheu,</hi> and by the Germans <hi>Funs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirchen;</hi> but of any Proteſtant Quinq' Eccleſian Elders, I never heard or read of before this: Neither know I what he can meane by them, but the five independent Miniſters of the Aſſembly, whom hitherto I never heard deſigned by ſuch a name or title; and if theſe be they, I anſwer, that the Commiſſioners ſay not that they are darke, but thoſe <hi>who in the dark are afraid of that which they know not.</hi> Now light may be in darkneſſe; Neither can he apply this to theſe Presbyters or to himſelfe, unleſſe he finde in himſelfe there be <hi>conſcia mens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners adde (for explication of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) <hi>and ſuffer their affections to run before their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Well-willer replieth: <hi>Are we not morall men (vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas vult, ut intellectus intelligit) to underſtand firſt, and affect after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Maſter Well-willer, if your affections may be judged of by your actions, certainly they are ſo indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that they will not be tyed, according to the rules of Philoſophy, to depend upon the underſtanding, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand</hi> firſt, &amp; to <hi>affect</hi> after: and we can tel you, S<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> from Scripture, that if a man be not a very gracious (I ſay not a morall) man, he will readily <hi>underſtand</hi> as he <hi>affects,</hi> rather then <hi>affect</hi> as he <hi>underſtands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That maxime of Philoſophy ſtriketh not at all at the Commiſſioners expreſſion: they ſay that their <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:111091:12"/>run before their <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and not that their <hi>will</hi> runs before their <hi>underſtanding:</hi> Now <hi>will</hi> and <hi>affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> be two things; the one in the Reaſonable ſoule, the other in the Appetite; unleſſe with the old Philoſophers, as <hi>Ariſtotler</hi> elateth of them,<note place="margin">l. 3 de Anima, cap. 3. tex. 150.</note> ye will confound <hi>mente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſu,</hi> and conſequently <hi>voluntatem cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appetitu,</hi> &amp; ſo make mans ſoul mortall, as the late Author of the <hi>Mortality of the Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Or if ye take the affection in a more large, but leſſe proper ſignification, as it ſignifieth alſo the inclinations and movements of the will, then they underſtand not thereby the conſulted, deliberated, &amp; adviſed, but the raſh inconſiderate, precipitate, and indeliberate actions of the <hi>will,</hi> otherwiſe called the firſt movements of the wil <hi>motus primo primi, qui omne judicium rationis antevertunt,</hi> which attend not, but prevent the judgement of reaſon. <hi>i. e.</hi> the deliberation and examen of the underſtanding; And in theſe movements it is certain that the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> goes before the underſtanding; for in ſuch movements the ſenſitive ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite which is led by the ſenſe, miſleadeth the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; not <hi>formally,</hi> but <hi>objectivè,</hi> in ſo far forth as drawing with it the phanſie or imagination, whoſe phantaſmata or images determine the underſtanding in its judgement, &amp; it being ſo determined, ſuddenly without any morall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation determineth the will; but ſo the will is ſaid to affect without judgement, i. e. without that deliberative judgement, which is neceſſary to your morall man, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the morall actions of his will: and in this ſenſe the Poet ſaid, <hi>Scilicet inſano nemo in amore videt. Boetius</hi> the Martyr: <hi>Quis leges det amantibus? major lex amor eſt ſibi.</hi> And <hi>Seneca: Quod ratio poſcit, vincit; at regnat furor, Potenſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tota mente dominatur Deus.</hi> So <hi>Ariſtotle: Qualis quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt, talis ei finis eſſe videtur, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eadem videntur a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantibus
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111091:12"/>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dio habentibus.</hi> So ſhould you have taken this judicious expreſſion of the Commiſſioners. 3. <hi>Item,</hi> the <hi>will</hi> in <hi>actionibus ſuis imperatis,</hi> whereof ſome be acts of the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> muſt goe before the <hi>underſtanding;</hi> for the <hi>underſtanding</hi> muſt command, before that the <hi>underſtanding</hi> can obey. 4. The <hi>Actions</hi> of the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> that are not <hi>involuntary,</hi> but <hi>voluntary,</hi> or wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, muſt follow the <hi>will,</hi> for <hi>voluntarium</hi> belongeth firſt to the will, and by the will to the other faculties. 5. Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall ſinne alſo, ill habitudes, cuſtomes, and violent paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hinder the will from following the underſtanding, and make it ſome times to miſcarry againſt the light of the underſtanding. 6. Albeit the <hi>will</hi> in its movements preſuppoſes neceſſarily ſome <hi>judgement</hi> of the <hi>underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> yet this <hi>judgement</hi> neceſſarily preſuppoſed, moves it not neceſſarily, for it may be as well moved and directed by another judgement, (that moveth it not) to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary action, whereunto it is not moved or directed, as it is this or that judgement, that actually moveth and directeth it to this, or that action in effect. 7. And if you beleeve that the <hi>underſtanding</hi> moveth the <hi>will</hi> neceſſarily, then in our <hi>Regeneration</hi> it ſhould ſuffice, that the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> alone ſhould be <hi>renewed,</hi> for it ſhould neceſſarily draw the <hi>will</hi> after it, which cannot be, ſince Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcateth no leſſe the renovation of the <hi>will,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heart, than that of the <hi>underſtanding.</hi> 8. A mans <hi>Regeneration</hi> ſhould conſiſt in <hi>Faith</hi> alone, without <hi>Charity</hi> which likewiſe cannot hold; for howſoever a man be <hi>juſtified</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> alone, without <hi>Charity,</hi> yet is he not <hi>regenerated</hi> by <hi>Faith</hi> alone, without <hi>Charity.</hi> 9. A man being endowed with <hi>intellectuall habitudes,</hi> ſhould not ſtand in need of <hi>Morall vertues</hi> to perfect the <hi>Will;</hi> but to be, as you call it, a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111091:13"/>or rather a good man morally, it ſhould ſuffice to be prudent; and ſo <hi>morall</hi> vertues ſhould have their ſeate in the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> and be nothing elſe but <hi>Sciences,</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or prudences, which was the opinion of <hi>Socrates,</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally blamed by all Philoſophers. 10. And finally, howſoever the <hi>Will</hi> is evermore ruled by ſome judgment, yet that finall judgement, that ruleth it, or that <hi>judicium ultimum,</hi> and <hi>practicè practicum,</hi> that ruleth humane acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dependeth of the <hi>Will,</hi> as the Philoſophers and Schoolemen both hold. And ſo much touching this quarrell, which you here begged with your vaine Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, ſo much condemned by S. <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 3 §. 1. <hi>Wherein,</hi> ſay you, <hi>hath appeared this prepoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſſe toward you, whiles the Apologie ſmiles upon you, and ſweetly calleth you and Holland by name the more reformed Churches? Doe you give them one ſuch a kinde word in all your Reply?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here it ſeemeth, that this Well-willer would paction with the Commiſſioners for an interchange of Commendations: but they have already anſwered, that they cannot praiſe you, but ſo far forth as truth will ſuffer them, <hi>p.</hi> 2. §. 2. Neither doe they deny, but the Reformed Churches Diſcipline may have need of reformation, as their faith, that is ſtill growing <hi>from faith to faith;</hi> but from thence it followeth no more, that it is erronious, then that their faith is ſo. And here it is to be noted, how cloſely this originall ſinne in arguing evermore <hi>à Poſſe ad Eſſe,</hi> ſticketh to this as to all other Independenters bones. Let him ſhew, wherein either the Scots, or other Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Churches need Reformation: Let him prove, that their Government is but a contrived Epiſcopacie; that it is ſuch as maketh all Reformed Churches unworthy of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111091:13"/>Independenters communion; that their owne Churches are endowed with ſuch a Seraphicall perfection, and ours ſo corrupt, that they dare no more communicate with us, then the Phariſes thought they could doe with the people: <hi>item,</hi> that there is no ſubordination in Eccleſiaſticall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatories; That men are not Church members, before they be admitted by a Church Covenant diſtinct from the Covenant of Grace. If that he can doe this, it will be more to the purpoſe then all theſe ridiculous exclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and complaints: We deſire arguments, and no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliments.</p>
            <p>P. 3. S. 2. <hi>Not to make, &amp;c.</hi> This is very dangerous, and may breed, if it have not already, as many Sects of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticts, Scepticts, Aporeticts, and Pyrrhoniens amongſt you, as were in former times amongſt the Philoſophers, no leſſe deſtructive of all faith and ſetled Eccleſiaſticall lawes, then theirs were of all Sciences; and therefore both ſo juſtly branded by the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p>There is <hi>one thing more, that maketh the Apologiſts more confident of their candor, in that their Apologie received ſo great an Approbation from ſo pious and learned a man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> How confident the Commiſſioners may be of their candor, and ye ſhould be of yours, it were better to heare it of the Aſſembly then of you, ſince <hi>it</hi> is more to be believed in this cauſe, then ye in judging of your ſelves. And as for that Approbation, it was but from one man. 2. It was not approved by the whole Aſſembly, as was that of the <hi>Reformation cleared,</hi> which was approved by that ſame very learned man alſo. 3. And he by that very approbation did ſolemnly condemne your Apologeticall Narration. 4. Neither approved he the ſubſtance, but ſome circumſtances of your Apologie, viz. its modeſtie,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111091:14"/>&amp;c. wherein he might be very eaſily deceived. <hi>Item,</hi> your Communicableneſſe, hoping better of you than appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly he will find; and compatibleneſſe with Magiſtracy, which hitherto is not fully proved. 5. Whether he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved all that ye preſented to him at firſt in your Booke, your ſelves know beſt: if not, we have not as yet your opinion, till according to exigence of time, &amp;c. you give the world a ſecond edition of it, and then ye may tell us newes of your candor. 6. Neither could he judge of your candor, ſince he could no way judge of your heart, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly whether your writ was conſona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to your words, and your words to your heart. Beſides all this, in that Approbation he declareth his averſion from yours, and inclination towards the Presbyterian Government: So as this mans braine ſeemeth of a very ſtrange temper, in citing for him, that, which is ſo directly againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As on the other ſide, though the Aſſembly voted you thankes, yet was it only for the Bookes you gave them not for the Reply, as it was expreſſed (to that effect) in the Vote, if obſervation faile not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This cannot but be moſt untrue: 1. for the Aſſembly voted them no thankes for the books, till all the Members thereof had read &amp; conſidered the ſame, &amp; were extreamely well ſatisfied with the contents thereof. 2. He would make this grave Aſſembly very ridiculous, (to ſay no more) if it had nothing elſe to doe, but to imploy ſo much time in voting thankes for ſo ſmall a matter, <hi>viz.</hi> for a two-penny book. 3. If it be ſo, wherefore voted it not thankes for the <hi>Apologeticall Narration,</hi> which was a great deale bigger, and ſold 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>? 4. Here according to your judgement, it cannot eſcape the blame of great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111091:14"/>towards the Apologizers, whereof yee will doe well to admoniſh it. 5. For feare your obſervation faile you, I pray you looke the Act, and afterwards you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not (if you have any candor) but in imitation of S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> diſabuſe the world by ſome booke of Retractations, which here you abuſe by this your falſe obſervation.</p>
            <p>And thus far I came with my reaſons grounded upon ſome generall, but very certaine relations, concerning the Aſſemblies ſpeech, in giving thankes to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Church of Scotland for their Reply to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologeticall Narration: but ſince this my Book hath been ended, upon more particular information I adde theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing reaſons. 8. The Aſſembly in thanking them for it calleth it a very learned and pious piece, which is not a praiſe of two ſheets of paper and a little inke; but alſo of the matter it containeth. 9. It was there ſaid, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſefull for this time, when the Aſſembly hath vowed and covenanted to come as neare as they can, in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Church unto that of other Reformed Churches, and namely of that of Scotland, taking ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more Gods Word for their firſt patterne and infallible rule of direction. 10. They are thanked for it, becauſe it refuteth ſome unworthy aſperſions, that ſome have faſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned upon the Government of the Reformed Churches; now who can thoſe be, judge you Sir. If here the one be thanked, I may probably ſay, the other getteth little thanks for his paines. 11. The Aſſembly rejoyceth at the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away of thoſe aſperſions, yea unworthy aſperſions, as they are termed by them. 12. The Authors of ſuch fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie aſperſions were there ſaid to affect wayes of their owne: now what can be thoſe wayes that be their owne, ſince they are not called Gods wayes, judge yee againe?
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111091:15"/>13. They are paralleled there with Biſhops, being both two oppoſite enemies to the Government of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, the Biſhops ſaying, no Biſhop, no King, and the others, that the Reformed Churches gave not the Civill Magiſtrate his due; which I interpret to bee, as if the one ſaid, a King cannot be without a Biſhop, and the other, a King cannot bee with Presbyteriall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 14. Becauſe it was there ſaid, that it was neceſſary to vindicate the Churches of God from ſo unjuſt imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. 15. Becauſe the Aſſembly like wiſe men commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very highly the ſincerity, gravity, and ingenuity of the Book. 16. Becauſe the Synod declareth, how it acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth it ſelf very much beholden to the Commiſſioners for the vindication of their owne and other Proteſtant Churches. 17. It is called a temperate and ſeaſonable vindication. 18. The Aſſembly ſaith in name of all the Churches of this Kingdome, that they deſire to keep with them all and that of Scotland a more arct Communion and uniformity in the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt. 19. The Aſſembly declareth there, that they had a very high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of the Church of Scotland. 20. It commended alſo the Commiſſioners for their judicious and grave diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the Aſſembly, which contributed much to the foreſaid Uniformitie with all the Proteſtant Churches. And all this I have deduced at length, not onely to refute this untruth, but many others, heretofore and hereafter, which this unworthy Pamphleter caſteth upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, yea upon all our Churches, to kindle a fire of Diviſion betwixt the Civill Magiſtrate and them, in theſe moſt calamitous times, when both Church and State are in combuſtion already. But after ſuch evident untruths, he addeth, <hi>if obſervation faile not:</hi> Here he ſeemeth to make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111091:15"/>us believe, that the Author of this Pamphlet is one of the Members of the Aſſembly, or that ſome Member of the Aſſembly has dealt treacherouſly and perfidiouſly with the Aſſembly, in pinning upon them ſuch an Act, flatly contrary to their formall expreſſions, (for none but ſome Member of the Aſſembly could make any ſuch obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) But of this I will ſay nothing, it being a matter of higher concernment. I beleeve rather that the Author of this Booke is minded, <hi>in principio, medio, &amp; fine,</hi> to be like to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 4. §. 1. We read nothing elſe but of the Independen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters admirations (which Philoſophers call the daughter of ignorance) and ſome of their thoughts and judgements, as if they were giving an account of their Creed: as <hi>p.</hi> 2. we read nothing but <hi>Interjections</hi> of lamentation, <hi>ah, oh,</hi> &amp;c. of <hi>holy and gracious men:</hi> whereas we crave ſome <hi>quia's, ergo's,</hi> or other rationall <hi>Conjunctions;</hi> whereunto we cannot better reply, then did <hi>Scotus</hi> to a Doctor of the <hi>Sorbone</hi> in <hi>Paris:</hi> This Doctor when he could not anſwer <hi>Scotus</hi> his argument by Reaſon, ſaid evermore, <hi>Reſpondeo cum Sancto Doctore: Cum S. Doctore,</hi> replied the other, <hi>ſi ſanctus oret pro nobis, ſi Doctor, reſpondeat ad argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum:</hi> ſo we to you; If thoſe men among you be holy, let them cry, <hi>ah,</hi> for their ſinnes, and pray to God for Gods Church, but let Doctors propound and anſwer ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments: but this man reaſoneth not, but giveth out Sentences, as if he were ſome Iudge of one of the Benches. You doe but imagine and fancie whatſoever you ſay in this Section of your <hi>imagination</hi> of the Commiſſioners <hi>extr ajudiciall and eccentricall Act:</hi> your <hi>acts</hi> may rather ſeeme Eccentricall <hi>ſecundum quid</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centricall <hi>ſecundum quid</hi> with <hi>Oxford,</hi> where, me thinkes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111091:16"/>they have more regard a great deale to your tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, then to thoſe of the Commiſſioners; Neither can any mortall man hinder ſo <hi>independent imaginations.</hi> It hath been already proved, that you have given the firſt, ſecond, and third blow, and in your Apologeticall Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration you threatned yet another: your judgement is ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly erronious, in thinking that this was intended to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unite the Presbiterians from others, <hi>i. e.</hi> from Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denters (ſince no others can well be thought upon, all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orthodox Churches, and all the Synod being no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) for their intention is altogether to unite you with them. Neither are there, for any thing we know, any that diſunite you from them, or them from you, ſave your ſelves onely.</p>
            <p>P. 4. §. 3. This well willer is very impertinent in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving againſt the Commiſſioners, that <hi>Viſibility and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are not eſſentiall notes of a true Church,</hi> which they, I beleeve, never thought, I am ſure never ſaid. And yet I muſt ſay, that howſoever <hi>viſibility</hi> be not <hi>eſſentiall</hi> to a true Church, yet it is <hi>eſſentiall to a true viſible Church,</hi> whereof we all diſpute here. And howſoever of a <hi>true Church</hi> wee cannot inferre <hi>viſibility,</hi> yet from <hi>true viſibility</hi> we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a <hi>true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 5. §. 1. <hi>He bleſſeth God, that God hath made a Rehoboth for the Scots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And God willing wee ſhall bee fruitfull in the Land as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and we pray God he and his be not as the <hi>Herdſmen of Gerar,</hi> even ſtriving with our Herdſmen of <hi>Iſaac.</hi> If we have a Rehoboth, wherefore will yee not drinke of our Spring? wherefore (to uſe your termes) will ye not <hi>jumpe</hi> with us? or if yee will not, ye may be gone as <hi>Lot</hi> with your Paſtours, and ſeparate your ſelves from <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111091:16"/>
            <p> Ibid. <hi>Who can hinder the windes, if they blow, and bring blacke weather from the North, or Weſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. No true Engliſh hearts have made any ſuch judgement of the Northerly windes theſe three yeares laſt paſt. How much trulier might it bee ſaid of a few Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſticall ſpirits, with their <hi>Vbi habitas amica mea in meridie?</hi> that trouble their mother Church, eſteeming all her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unworthy of their Communion.</p>
            <p>Pag. 5. §. 3. Ye come up me thinkes ſomewhat lamely with your Catalogue of Prophets. 1. For onely ye have one <hi>Brightman,</hi> and yet none of yours, hee is of ours; for he preferreth the Scots Church, conſtituted of Parochiall, Claſſicall, and Synodall Aſſemblies, before all other, or at leaſt poſtpones it to no others. 2. Neither in expoſing the Prophecies of Scripture according to Scripture, can he be ſaid to have had the gift of Prophecie, ſince his expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions were not infallible: for ſo every true Miniſter of the Goſpel ſhould be a Prophet.</p>
            <p>As lamely came ye up with your Martyrs. 1. For when you call it a civill death or Martyrdome, the word Civill is <hi>terminus diminuens aut alienans,</hi> which diminiſhes, or rather transfers it from a proper to an uncouth or impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſignification; as the word dead, when I ſay <hi>Peter</hi> is a dead man, for a dead man is not a man, i. e. a living man, in making it a civill and improper death, or Martyrdome; ye make it leſſe then that of the Presbyterians, which was reall: And ſo indeed it is, for wee finde you evermore in all the ſtory flying reall Martyrdome, rather then attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it. 2. It is alſo a maxime in Logicke, that <hi>à termino di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minuto vel alienato non argumentamúr ad eundèm terminum abſolutè acceptum:</hi> So this your argument muſt be capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in arguing, that yee dye a civill death, or are civilly
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111091:17"/>Martyrs. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ye are Martyrs. It is no better then to ſay, There is a golden Calfe: <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is a Calfe.</p>
            <p>P. 6. §. 3. I ſay, to receive and practiſe ſome things uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received in the Reformed Churches, and not to receive or practiſe others, but either to reject them openly, or cunningly to profeſſe that yee retaine <hi>your</hi> judgement, ſeeke <hi>for further-light,</hi> or doubt as the <hi>Ephectici, Sceptici &amp; Pyrrhonii,</hi> ſufficeth not to make you parts of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches. 1. For by the ſame reaſon the Donatiſts ſhould have beene parts of the Orthodox Churches of their time. 2. Item, the univerſall Reformed Church in reſpect of its externall form is a <hi>totum homogeneum,</hi> which may bee attributed <hi>in recto</hi> to all the parts or particular Churches thereof, which could not be, if ſome particular Churches differed in ſo many practices from all the reſt. As for your inſtance of the Church of Scotland, that the Commiſſioners ſay, it may receive further Reformation; that may be underſtood <hi>in moribus, ſed non in morum legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> in manners and practice, but not in Rules of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline touching practice. Or if it bee taken of Rules or Lawes, it is not in the Rules or Lawes that concerne the eſſentiall or principall integrant parts of Diſcipline, but things meerly accidentall, as they expound themſelves, by the example of faith, which the beſt Chriſtian in the world may have, which evermore is perfect eſſentially, and according to its integrant parts, in reſpect of its exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the principall parts of its object, how ever it may be imperfect, <hi>quoad entitatem intenſivam;</hi> and <hi>extenſivam accidentalem &amp; ratione partium minus principalium:</hi> ſo their Eccleſiaſticall Lawes may ever better and better bee put in execution, and augmented <hi>extenſivè,</hi> in reſpect of the accidentall and moſt inconſiderable parts of its <hi>object,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:111091:17"/>according to the exigence of time, places, and other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: But reade the Text and ye ſhall finde, that it ſaith no ſuch thing as this Doctor would draw out of it.</p>
            <p>P. 6. §. 4. To excuſe themſelves in calling all Orthodox and Reformed Churches Calvinians, the Well-willer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployeth all his wit, Rhetoricke, and Philoſophy. Here he beginneth againe with his Ah; cenſures the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for complaining of this nickname put upon them, and would faine perſwade them, that it is <hi>ad honores,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, that they are bound to thanke them for this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury they have done them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But 1. we have Saint <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly condemning ſuch names. 2. They who accept of them, hee calleth them carnall. 3. And willeth us not to accept of any name, but of his in whoſe we are baptized, <hi>viz.</hi> Chriſts. 4. For as he argueth us to be named Cephaiſts, Paulinians, or Apollonians: ſo may we to bee called Calvinians, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, &amp;c. is to make a Schiſm. 5. Becauſe all the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Churches have evermore refuſed it. 6. And only their enemies, Papiſts, and Lutherans ſtil pind this name upon us as opprobrious. 7. Since it is put upon us againſt our will, it cannot be good for us, at leaſt in our eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 8. For even good urged upon a man againſt his will is troubleſome, and a burden to him. 9. Beſides all this, we have the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> quoted by the Commiſſioners, who with us taketh Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> part againſt this Doctor. And hereupon commeth in according to his ordinary cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome his lamentable exclamations, his <hi>Ohs</hi> thrice reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, <hi>Oh unhappy conjunction; Oh heavy application; Oh coale blacke termes.</hi> Thoſe be termes of Rhetoricke, but not of Logicke. I like better of a <hi>quia,</hi> then of your <hi>Ah, oh, &amp;c.</hi> he will neither depend upon Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> nor upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111091:18"/>
               <hi>Hierom.</hi> But he will neither depend upon Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> nor any reaſon, but will argue againſt all, 1. That it is to diſtinguiſh us from more corrupted Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> forbiddeth ſuch names of diſtinction, and Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith; that it diſtinguiſhes the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church from the Church of Chriſt. But if ye will needs be diſtinguiſhing us, name us on Gods name by the names that we accept of, as by that of Orthodox, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, which our common enemies refuſe us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ob. <hi>It was uſed to decline the word Presbyterian, that leſſe offence might be taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. It is not neceſſary to name us by either the one or the other: and yet were it better to name the Proteſtant Churches Presbyterians, ſince this name is taken from the forme of their government.</p>
            <p>Ob. 3 I is a name of honour.</p>
            <p>Anſw. We deſire not ſuch honours as are forbidden in Scripture, and that with ſuch a violent courteſie are urged upon us.</p>
            <p>Ob. 4. Papiſts diſgrace not themſelves in calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Catholickes: <hi>Ergo,</hi> No more doe the Apologiſts in calling us Calvinians, ſince they be ſuch themſelves.</p>
            <p>Anſw. I deny the conſequence, for the Catholicke Church is a terme of the Creed, Heb. <hi>Panegyris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for your ſelfe yee may take what names pleaſe you beſt, yet deſire wee you to take none that be forbidden in Scripture: Neither heard wee ever that yee accepted it before this preſent, and that as we conceive to excuſe your ſelves, rather then that you have any great minde to it yet.</p>
            <p>Afterwards P. 7. the Doctor calleth this expreſſion or reaſon of the Commiſſioners <hi>Coloquintida,</hi> or <hi>Colocynthis, q.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Dogges meat, but of what Dogs I know not,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111091:18"/>but of ſuch as accept of ſuch names; if it be dogs meat, then the Apoſtle and S. <hi>Hierome</hi> have given you dogges meat. This injury and dogged anſwer ſtriketh no leſſe at S. <hi>Paul</hi> and S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> then at the Commiſſioners: if <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynthis</hi> be <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe it ſerveth for a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or purgation for the belly, to purge all petui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, bilious and melancholious humours, we pray God it may worke well upon you, and that this be the laſt vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit againſt the Reformed Churches. If it be applied outwardly, it killeth the fruit, <hi>&amp; abortum parit: utinam vobis abortum p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riat;</hi> I pray God againe it may cauſe you abortiveneſſe, and make you caſt your unhappy fruits, before they come to maturitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet, as if in revenge, you ding the words of [Separation] and [Browniſts] againſt the Apologiſts, as if you had forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, or di<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intend to miſapply what you had ſaid in the next line afore quoted out of Hierome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Te fruſtra Augurium vani docuere parentes.</hi> Sir, you are no good Diviner, for it is not the Apologiſts, but the Browniſts, whom they call the Separation, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth moſt expreſly by their own words: <hi>The Seperation may be well allowed to be called Browniſts.</hi> This therefore is but a meere calumny that ye pin upon them, to the end that thereupon ye may bewaile and lament your conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and great oppreſſion before the people, which take your words upon credit: but the more to blame a great deale you are, that ſo ordinarily deceive their eaſie cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie. And truly if ye could quit this kinde of reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the reſt of the matter you ſtuffe your Booke with, would be found very weake. And yet I muſt ſay of my ſelfe, what elſewhere I have ever ſaid, that ye are really Separatiſts, ſince ye ſeparate your ſelves from the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111091:19"/>communion of all other Orthodox Churches, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeming them unworthy of your Communion. So by this time any one may ſee, they want not memory in what they ſay, but you judgement to underſtand them, or honeſtie at leaſt to relate faithfully what they ſay. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo dealt with them for want of ſome other Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt, he ſetteth forth the praiſes of his own vertues, <hi>viz.</hi> his great patience and mercy towards them. <hi>Were it not for patience, nay that would hardly doe it; were it not for reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of you and your Nation, a home anſwer would be ſhaped to ſuch a miſhapen miſpriſion. But to love is to live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Your patience, Sir, is very weak, yea ſcarcely <hi>in gradu continentiae,</hi> ſince it can hardly ſo command your choler and deſire of revenge againſt a pretended and ſo imaginarie an offence. 2. So ſurely muſt be your other vertues, and conſequently your Reverence; for there is a neceſſary connexion betwixt them all, at leaſt <hi>in gradu temperantiae,</hi> under the which they cannot abſolutely have the name of vertues. 3. Reverence is a vertue, whereby we give honour to vertuous perſons, and feare to offend them, becauſe of their vertues, merits or dignitie: If ſo, I pray what Reverence is it, ſo to calumniate them as you have done? 4. Or if they be ſuch as you have repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to be, then can they not be the object of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſo this your Reverence is no reall vertue. 5. As for the Reverence ye carry to our Nation, I will but put you in minde of the good eſteeme you have of it; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very windy and unluckie for Engliſh men. Your words are, <hi>Who can hinder the winds, if they blow, and bring black weather out of the North or Weſt?</hi> If it be ſuch, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be thought worthy of any Reverence: ſo this, you ſay here, cannot be ſaid, but in deriſion of it, unleſſe you be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111091:19"/>content to give a lye to your ſelfe. But what ever be your judgement of your own Nation, or of ours; We thank God that they have ſuch eſteeme one of another, that you cannot much further or hinder it. As for my ſelfe; what <hi>Eraſmus Roterodamus</hi> ſaith of his <hi>Holland,</hi> that I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to our <hi>Scotland. Terra mihi ſemper &amp; celebranda &amp; veneranda, ut cui vitae hujus initia debeam: atque utinam illi nos tam poſsimus honeſtamento viciſs<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m eſſe, quam illa nobis non eſt poenitenda.</hi> Our Country, Sir, is an honour to us both, I pray God none of us be a diſhonour to our Countrey. And as for you, I may ſay, that when your Countrey and the Church of God therein (as many of your Countrey-men, very good Chriſtians and Patriots ſay) had moſt need of you, ye left it and neglected it; and at this preſent, when it ſtandeth in no need at all of you, ye returne againe unſent for, to vexe the Church of God, and to hinder Reformation in it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I anſwer: in matters of ſo high importance, ſo holy men as ye pretend to be, ſhould make no diſtinction of perſons, nor diſtinguiſh betwixt the Greek and the Schy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian: all ſhould be to you one in Chriſt; To <hi>love</hi> indeed is to <hi>live,</hi> if your love be ſuch as it ſhould be: but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>amantes ſunt amentes,</hi> and their love is rather a dreame then reall, when they dote more upon their owne fancies more then upon truth: <hi>Credimus an qui amant, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n qui ſibi ſomnia fingunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He addeth, that we <hi>muſt not ſet our houſes on fire to roſt our own egges. Anſw.</hi> Who doth it now in matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but the Independenters? <hi>Veſtrorum cauſa malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum vos eſtis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>P. 8. §. 1. We are glad that as ye diſavow the reſt, ſo ye do this, that ye intended not to touch the Church of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111091:20"/>in ſaying that <hi>ye had no Commonwealths to reare.</hi> Only this we ſay, that if ye ſay true, that then it was impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in: And as ye ſay, <hi>it might better bee underſtood of thoſe of New England, who had the Kings Patent for what they did in Policy, as Gods Word for Church Government.</hi> Onely here I obſerve, that you acknowledge the King and his Patent, onely in Policy, and Gods Word onely in Church government. Now I pray, then what more give ye to the Civill Magiſtrate, then other Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the point of Church Government? And as for Policy, no Reformed Churches ever medled with it, that I know of.</p>
            <p>P. 8. §. 3. If ye thought it not a bleſſing of God, or ſome good worthy of thankſgiving, <hi>not to bee engaged by educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or other wayes to any other of the Reformed Churches.</hi> This diſcourſe muſt be very impertinent, in bringing this for a reaſon, that your Diſcipline is good, or better, then that of all other Reformed Churches; for afterwards yee bring your ſelves in as ſpectators of all Churches and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplines, being of none your ſelves, but <hi>in abſtractione pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither ſay the Commiſſioners abſolutely, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologiſts <hi>were left to their owne private thoughts to bee mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by,</hi> but <hi>ex hypotheſi,</hi> that they were not engaged to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches; and truly no reaſonable man can thinke but they were ſo, ſince they ſay that in looking upon all Governments they were ſimple ſpectators; ſo that this Doctor for this extravagant ſenſe, ſo repugnant to the text, may be thought to have beene Graduate at Orleans.</p>
            <p>And ſince this Well-willer his profeſſion is <hi>to live to love</hi> the Commiſſioners, I ſhall onely note by the way what a rare and curious expreſſion he has found out to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111091:20"/>it by, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>they are men of a better ſpirit then the venemous Spider of envy.</hi> They are bound to thanke you Mr. Doctor of well-willing, for this pretty complement ye paſſe upon them.</p>
            <p>P. 9. § 3. As in all the reſt of his Booke, ſo here he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very cunningly to worke, evermore omitting what is moſt materiall in the Commiſſioners Booke. Hee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not a word to the number of Church Officers, or to their juſtification againſt the aſperſions laid upon them for Lay Elders, or their accuſation againſt the Independents, becauſe of their Laymen Preachers and Prophets &amp;c. All this he paſſeth over by a Doctorall priviledge, <hi>hic &amp; ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> terrarum tacendi.</hi> Onely he ſcratcheth at the proofe they bring for Presbyteries, Claſſes, and Synods: but refuteth it not; no more then hee doth the Arguments brought by Maſter <hi>Rhetherford, Guelaſpe,</hi> and others, taken from Gods Attributes, as 1. from his Goodneſſe, 2. Wiſedome, 3. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, 4. Providence, 5. from the nature of the Church, &amp;c. Item, from the Law of Nature, 6. from ſundry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences. 7. From the order eſtabliſhed in the Church of the Jewes. 8. From the practice of the Church in the times of the Apoſtles. 9. From Chriſts inſtitution in the New Teſtament. 10. From parity of reaſon or propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt a Pariſhionall Seſſion or Conſiſtory, and ſix or ſeven perſons in the reall Church thereof, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined Presbytery, as ye call it, and every one of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; peradventure two or three or ten thouſand Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Conſiſtories ſubject thereunto. 11. From the ends of the Church, 12. her Conſervation, Peace, &amp;c. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ye may happily heare more within a few dayes. In the meane time I pray you anſwer to what is written, and not to clude ſuch arguments with tales at Aſſizes, Wooll-packes,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111091:21"/>Cannon-ſhot. Bullets, Batteries, and termes of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline, wherewith we are not ſo well acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>P. 10. §. 3. Here it ſeemeth that this Doctor would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe the Apologizers, in ſaying that they <hi>give more to the Civill Magiſtrate, then the principles of the Presbytertall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment will ſuffer them to yeeld.</hi> As if it were rather ſaid by way of retaliation and in anger, then in truth, becauſe (as he ſaith) <hi>the peace-plea calleth them Independents.</hi> If it be ſo, 1. their paſſion is worthy of the others compaſſion. 2. But this ſhould not have made them to offend all the Reformed Churches, and eſpecially their Benefactors in the Netherlands, which are all Presbyterians. 3. All compariſons are alſo odious, eſpecially amongſt men well bred. 4. And yet howſoever they hate the name, yet they love dearely the thing ſignified by the name, and will depend of no Eccleſiaſticall Judicatory, yea (as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Obſervations and Annotations ſheweth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) not upon all the Churches of the world; and yet will that their Congregations depend of themſelves, who yet will depend upon no men in ſpirituall power or authority.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor ſaith, <hi>If upon a groſſe errour of another Church they (viz. Independent Churches) dare exerciſe only a non communion with it, then there is more left for the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to doe, then when you have excommunicated it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In excommunicating a private perſon, or a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church (when it can be done with leſſe hurt to the Church then is the good included therein) it leaveth all to be done by the Magiſtrate, that God has ordained him to doe, <hi>viz.</hi> in politicall government. <hi>Non auferet mortalia, quiregna dat coeleſtia.</hi> Neither requireth the godly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, our King or this Parliament any more: but ye are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111091:21"/>importune who will give him more then he requireth of you, or then either God or the Magiſtrate hath comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you. The French ſay of ſuch men, <hi>Il eſt valet du Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, ilfait plus que commandement.</hi> I will not here inſiſt upon your impertinency in denying the name of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication to non communion, and that great pride in not ſubmitting the judgement of five or ſix (ſome times) idle, yea (oftentimes) wicked felllowes, to the judgement of all the Divines and Churches of the world, in caſe they ſhould dogmatiſe and ſuſtein the moſt damnable hereſies of the world, and yet unto their judgement, however ſo contemptible a number, ye will ſubmit the judgement of all their Congregation, amounting peradventure to the number of many hundreds, (it may be) better men then themſelves. Neither is it enough to leave it to the Civill Magiſtrate; for his power is not ſpirituall: God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven an intrinſecall power to the Church, ſufficient for its ſpirituall end: the Civill Magiſtrate may be a Pagan, an Antichriſtian Chriſtian, an externall Chriſtian, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward enemy to the Church: he may be negligent in his charge, &amp;c. and is it credible, that in ſuch caſes God hath inſtituted no Diſcipline or Government to take order with offenders? But of this I need not to ſay any thing, this evaſion being ſo well, ſo evidently and briefly refuted in the Commiſſioners own words, which I pray the Reader to conſider, <hi>p.</hi> 21.22. if it pleaſe the Reader, he may have ſundry reaſons againſt this opinion in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations and Annotations upon the Apologeticall Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. It is an untruth alſo that the Doctor preſuppoſeth here, <hi>viz.</hi> that a Claſſicall Presbyterie is made up of many Miniſters and Lay men in the Kingdome of Scotland or among other Proteſtants; And falſe againe, that their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111091:22"/>Aſſemblies are made up of perſons <hi>partly Eccleſiaſticall &amp; partly civill,</hi> or that they there rule perſons partly Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, partly Civill: we ſay that there can be no ſuch perſons; for howſoever one perſon may have one charge Eccleſiaſticall, and another ſecular or Civill, yet is he not therefore a mixt perſon, neither be theſe ſeverall charges mixt, but diſtinguiſh'd in him, fince of the two there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'teth not any third Charge compounded of both, as in mixtions: but he exerciſes them both diſtinctly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, in ſuch a faſhion, that the one never concurreth to the function and operation of the other. By the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſhould follow, that the divers faculties of the ſoule, as the underſtanding, &amp; expulſive facultie in a man, ſhould be mixt together, ſince they be both in one ſoule, as the moſt part of Philoſophers hold. When a States-man ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as a member of an Eccleſiaſticall Aſſembly, he ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no wayes as a States-man, but as a Church-man: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgeth he a State-man or ſecular perſon in qualitie of a States-man, or of a ſecular perſon, but in qualitie of a member of the Church: So they judge not of civill mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters formally, as they are ſubject to the Civill Magiſtrates authority, but materially &amp; in ſo far as they are ſubject to a ſpirituall formality, or conduce to a ſpirituall end, under the which notion they belong not ordinarily to the Civill Magiſtrate, or <hi>per ſe &amp; intrinſcce,</hi> but <hi>per accidens &amp; extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſece.</hi> as all Orthodox Divines of the Reformed Churches do teach. But this is not all, for ſundry of the Independents have told us, that the Civill Magiſtrate, according to Gods Word, cannot puniſh any man for matters of Religion, how abominable ſoever his opinions be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 11. and 12. the Doctor will not anſwer, becauſe he hath not the Books at hand, and ſo ſhifts over the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111091:22"/>What he ſaith of <hi>Aerius,</hi> who held out againſt Biſhops, as our Reformed Churches doe, is not to the purpoſe: No more is this, That Councells may erre. Afterwards he telleth us, that French Miniſters (as <hi>Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymus</hi> as himſelfe) and the French Diſcipline is for the Independenters, but proveth it not; but ſuppoſeth that we ſhould take it upon his word, which we may not at any hand doe, till we ſee more candor and ſincerity in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. As for <hi>Merellus</hi> and ſome Miniſters of the French Church, excommunicated for their erronious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, or ill lives, and afterward aſſaulted the Diſcipline whereby they were ſentenced, if they have any ſuch for them, we envy them not ſuch brethren.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Commiſſioners, <hi>p.</hi> 18. of the <hi>Reformation cleated,</hi> mainteining the fidelity of the Reformers of the Scottiſh Church, ſay, that they deſerted not their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, nor caried away Churches with them, nor did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe any voluntary exile, but thought it a great ſpoile after that they were ſentenced to exile to ſave their lives, and to live with very ſmall meanes, farre from any friends to comfort them. This the Doctor applieth to the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendenters, of whom the Commiſſioners doe not ſpeake, but of their owne Miniſters: But ſince it is his pleaſure to doe ſo, I muſt ſay that hence it followeth, that their exile was a far greater ſuffering then that of the Independents: 1. for it was involuntary; but the more involuntary that any afflictions be, the greater they are; and the more voluntary they be, the leſte they be; for, <hi>poena debet eſſe moleſta &amp; involuntaria;</hi> but that which is voluntary, is not troubleſome. 2. That of the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents was accompanied with many friends and worldly meanes: ſo was not the other. 3. It may be doubted, if
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111091:23"/>Paſtours for their perſonall or particular perſecution may fly, without actuall compulſion, and the publick conſent of their Flock, ſince they are not in the Church in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of particular, but of publick perſons, and Heads of the Flock; Neither can that Text of Scripture helpe him, viz. <hi>When they perſecute you in one place, flie to another;</hi> for that is ſaid of particular, and not of publick perſons: or if it be ſaid of the Apoſtles, as to the Apoſtles, it holdeth not in particular Miniſters tyed to particular Churches, for they are tyed to their particular Churches, but ſo were not the Apoſtles, who were equally bound to teach all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the world, according to that ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Goe teach all Nations,</hi> Matth. 28.19. and ſo could never aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don their flock. And as for his Anſwer, <hi>that they hept themſelves for a reſerve, to aſsiſt the Church at their returne:</hi> I muſt ſay they were very provident in foreſeeing ſuch an extraordinary caſe, and prudent in preſerving of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whereas the others ſacrificed their lives for Chriſts truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 12. §. 3. and <hi>p.</hi> 13. §. 1. &amp; 2. the Doctor ſaith no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt that which the Commiſſioners ſay, and ſo approveth it: he applieth it to the Independenters, and denieth that they eſteeme ſo of Excommunication, viz. that <hi>to limit the cenſure of Excommunication, in matter of opinion, to the common and uncontroverted principles, and in the matter of manners to the common and univerſall practiſes of Chriſtianitie, and in both to the parties known light, is the dangerous opinion of the Arminians and Socinians, openeth a wide dore and proclaimeth libertie to all other practiſes and errors which are not fundamentall, and univerſally abhorred by all Chriſtians, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this he anſwereth with complaints, and ſaith, that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:111091:23"/>there is no argument here: But in this Laconick diſcourſe there be more arguments then he ſeeth. The firſt is,</p>
            <p>Arminians and Socinians opinions are not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>But to limit Excommunication in matters of opinion, &amp;c. is Arminians and Socinians opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is not to be received.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is:</p>
            <p>What openeth a doore, and proclaimeth libertle to all other practifes and errors, which are not funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, is not to be admitted.</p>
            <p>But to limit Excommunication, &amp;c. is ſuch, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is not to be admitted.</p>
            <p>The third is:</p>
            <p>An opinion univerſally abhorred by all Chriſtians, is not to be received.</p>
            <p>But to limit Excommunication, in matter of opinion to the common uncontroverted principles, and in matter of manners to the common and univerſall practiſes of Chriſtianitle, and in both to the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties known light, (viz. of Nature or of Grace,) is an opinion univerſally abhorred by all Chriſtians, <hi>Ergo,</hi> to limit Excommunication, &amp;c. is not to be admitted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Doctrine that tendeth to the overthrow of the Reformed Religion, is not to be received.</p>
            <p>But to limit excommunication, &amp;c. tendeth to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow of the Reformed Religion, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is not to be received.</p>
            <p>To theſe Arguments he anſwereth not formally, neither to the matter nor to the forme; and no wonder, for he could not obſerve them. Only to the end he may ſeeme
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111091:24"/>not to have anſwer'd nothing at all, he telleth us, that <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Infidels doe not practiſe:</hi> But how is that to the purpoſe? ſince in all the Commiſſioners Diſcourſe there is not one word of Pagans or Infidels. 2. He anſwereth that Papiſts, Prelates, Socinians, Arminians, Browniſts, and Separatiſts, doe not hold ſome common truths with Chriſtians. But to what purpoſe he ſaith this, I know not: if it be to prove, that they may be excommunicated, we deny it not; but ſay, that to hold ſuch an opinion, is Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minianiſme, Socinianiſme, &amp;c. <hi>i. e.</hi> an Arminian or Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian opinion, whereunto he anſwereth not. Againe, by Socinians, Arminians, &amp;c. either he underſtandeth thoſe who are not borne in the Church, and who profeſſe not our Religion; or thoſe who are borne in the Church, and profeſſe our Religion: If the firſt, they cannot be excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, ſince they are not, nor ever were of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion: if the laſt, it is true, they may be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; but that is not the queſtion: but whether this be not Socinianiſme and Arminianiſme, viz. to limit Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication in matter of Opinion to the common and uncontroverted principles, and in matter of Manners to the univerſall practiſes of Chriſtianity. <hi>Item,</hi> whether this openeth not a doore to all other errors and practiſes, as they ſay?</p>
            <p>After this, when he can anſwer nothing, he returneth unto his ordinary lamentations, that they are compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Infidels, &amp;c. But the Commiſſioners ſerve not themſelves of bare compariſons, as ye uſe to doe, but with ſolid Arguments, which prove you clearely what they ſay: neither are ye compared by them with Seperatiſts, but I prove you to be ſuch, for ſeparating your ſelves from the reformed Churches Sacramental communion; neither are
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111091:24"/>ye compared with Browniſts, &amp;c. for conforming of Church Government with Scripture, as ye pretend, but for perverting of it againſt Scripture; wherefore all theſe your complaints are nothing elſe but calumnies, that yee caſt upon the Church of Chriſt, evermore ſophiſticating with your captions of <hi>non cauſa ut cauſa,</hi> according to the ordinary cuſtome of your Sect.</p>
            <p>And I pray this Doctor, what if a man become brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and have the light of his underſtanding altogether corrupted, ſo as to deny that there is any ſinne againſt the light of Nature? ſhall he not be excommunicated for it? ſhall his ignorance excuſe him? is not his ignorance a ſin, and eſpecially when it is concomitant or ſubſequent to ſome other ſinne or action of the will? when he has pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it to himſelfe, or when he uſed not morall diligence enough to chaſe it away? ſhall, or can the ignorance of the Law, or of his duty, which hee is bound to know, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him, or free him from excommunication? Is not that Socinianiſme, Arminianiſme, judge ye Maſter Doctor? and anſwer not with complaints, &amp; lamentable Interjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if you would rather be pitied then bound to prove any thing ye ſay; pay us not with generalities, and <hi>Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duum vagums,</hi> but <hi>ſignatums.</hi> Anſwer I pray you to the point.</p>
            <p>All the authority that this Maſter Doctor Well-willer can bring for himſelfe, <hi>p.</hi> 11. and 12. is a <hi>Morellus,</hi> and ſome other excommunicated Miniſters in France, which yet he hath borrowed from the cleared Reformation.</p>
            <p>As for that which he ſaith, <hi>p.</hi> 13. §. 2. <hi>that a Biſhop is a Presbytery contracted; and a Presbytery a Biſhop diffuſed:</hi> 1. It is but one of the Separatiſts ordinary jeeres againſt Presbyterian Government. 2. They prove it not. 3. The
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111091:25"/>Commiſſioners anſwer it, <hi>p.</hi> 25. 4. And if it were ſo, yet Presbyterian Ariſtocracie ſhould bee admitted, ſince it is Gods ordinance, but nor Epiſcopacy, ſince it is not Gods ordinance. 5. Amongſt the Helvetians, if one man ſhould goe and contrive into his owne perſon all the authority, which is diffuſed amongſt all the Rulers there, thinke you that they would endure him, or rather not put him to death, as a Tyrant and a Traytor, according to his deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? The very contrivance of authority into one perſon, which God hath diffuſed in many, is unjuſt and tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call in Gods Church.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor objecteth, that in forbearing Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication (I beleeve he underſtandeth the greater) they leave more to the Magiſtrate then the Presbyterie doth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This the Doctor ſaith, but proveth it not: and therefore we deny it with the like facility that he propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it: our reaſon is, becauſe when a man is excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, the Civill Magiſtrate ceaſeth not for all that to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him civilly: for the Presbyterie by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion exileth or caſteth him out of the Church ſociety: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding which he remaineth in the State ſociety: and if his ſinne be againſt the State, and deſerve it, the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may exile him, and caſt him out of the State ſociety, or of the Kingdome, but not out of the Church, no more then the Church may caſt him out of the Kingdom. As for your compariſons in ſaying that it is not an Engliſh heart that ſpeaketh ſo, it is but a ſophiſticall evaſion, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly to clude their argument, whereunto you cannot bring ſo much as a probable ſolution: ſo you grant what they ſay. Neither is our diſpute here about Engliſh, Scots, or French, but about Chriſtian hearts and conſciences: It is a ſhame to an Engliſh man to be Author of Schiſme
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111091:25"/>in his owne Country, when Strangers imploy all their endeavours for union and peace, both in Church and Common-wealth. But this I leave, and pray you to tell us what ye give more to the Civill Magiſtrate then we? whether it be an Eccleſiaſticall or Civill power, and wherein? whether to judge in matter of Doctrine or Diſcipline? Remember, Sir, that in ſpeaking of New England,<note place="margin">P. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> you give them nothing elſe but <hi>Gods word</hi> for <hi>Church Government,</hi> and <hi>the Kings patent for what they did in Policie;</hi> and tell us if ever they followed the Kings or his Councels directions in Church Policie. <hi>Item,</hi> tell us whether it is the Civill Magiſtrate, or the Church Officers part to erect Church Government, and to make the Lawes thereof; to judge according to the ſame, and to put them in execution &amp;c?</p>
            <p>Here he telleth us alſo, or objecteth, that Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <hi>hath need of better grounds then mens ſinning of ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity or ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So the ignorance of Jeſus Chriſt, and deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his merits ſhould not incur the ſentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication.</p>
            <p>Hee objecteth, that <hi>the puniſhment of Excommunication for ſmall faults will make the puniſhment at laſt ſmall in the eyes of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, but is it the doctrine of the Reformed Churches that it ſhould be inflicted for ſmall faults?</p>
            <p>But to cleare more this matter, two things are needfull to be expounded: the firſt is, what the Independents un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by <hi>great ſinnes?</hi> the ſecond, what they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the parties <hi>knowne light:</hi> thirdly, what by <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity:</hi> fourthly, what by <hi>common received practices</hi> of Chriſtianity: fiftly, what by the <hi>Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt, a <hi>ſinne</hi> may be <hi>great</hi> either <hi>quoad eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:111091:26"/>or <hi>quoad entitatem,</hi> according to its eſſence or entity, or as it were its quantity. That <hi>ſinne</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>greater</hi> then another according to its <hi>eſſence,</hi> the <hi>ſpecies</hi> whereof degenerateth moſt from the <hi>divine Rule of Gods Law,</hi> ſuch as be the ſins, that are greateſt in regard of their object; ſo it is a <hi>greater ſinne</hi> to offend God then man, becauſe it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth in it ſelfe a greater objective deformity, then the other. But a <hi>ſinne</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> then another according to its <hi>entity</hi> or <hi>quantity,</hi> that has greater <hi>extenſion, intenſion, or duration,</hi> i. e. more parts, more degrees, and of a longer continuance then another: By extenſion, or more parts, I underſtand either objective, or formall parts, <hi>viz.</hi> when a <hi>ſinne</hi> is committed againſt <hi>more perſons</hi> as the ſinne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt twenty is greater then that committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt two; or has more <hi>materiall objects,</hi> as when one ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth more money, <hi>viz.</hi> two pound, it is a greater finne then to ſteale two pence: So it is a <hi>greater ſinne</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>formall perts,</hi> or <hi>acts</hi> wherein formally ſin conſifteth, if they be taken <hi>in concreto,</hi> when a man returneth oftentimes to the ſame ſinne, as hee who ſtealeth ten times is a farre greater ſinner, then he that ſtealeth but only once.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the <hi>intention</hi> or <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>ſinne,</hi> that ſinne is greater then another wherein there be more <hi>degrees,</hi> as when it is committed more willingly, with greaterliberty, with greater violence, with greater knowledge; Item, by him that hath greater helpes of grace, or of nature to reſiſt it, and to produce the oppoſite effects of vertue. Finally, that <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>greater</hi> then another in <hi>duration,</hi> that continueth longer: So a <hi>ſin</hi> may be greater then another <hi>quoad eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> and leſſe <hi>quoadentitatem,</hi> or eſſentially greater, but entitatively or in quantity leſſe then another: and on the contrary greater then another <hi>quoad entitatem,</hi> or in regard of its quantity, but not greater eſſentially. For example, if a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111091:26"/>man ſin againſt the precepts of the firſt Table, in not loving God with all his heart, &amp; be ſory therefore; and againſt his Father, not onely in not loving him as himſelfe, but alſo in abuſing him willingly, and offering him violence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any remorſe of conſcience, the firſt <hi>ſinne</hi> is <hi>greater eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentialiter,</hi> but the <hi>laſt</hi> is <hi>greater entitativè:</hi> ſo ſome Schoolemen ſay, that <hi>faith</hi> is more <hi>certaine</hi> then any <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſcience quoad eſſentiam,</hi> but that <hi>naturall ſciences</hi> and the <hi>habitudes</hi> of <hi>naturall principles</hi> are more <hi>certaine quoad en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titatem:</hi> and this diſtinction being obſerved, it may ſo fall out, that a <hi>ſin</hi> that is <hi>greater eſſentially</hi> may not deſerve Excommunication, and that which is <hi>leſse,</hi> deſerve it: ſo that this Maxime of the Independenters will not hold u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>parties known light or knowledge,</hi> it is either <hi>Speculative</hi> which of it ſelf directeth not the <hi>will</hi> in its pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes or actions, as to know that there is <hi>three Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Trinity;</hi> or <hi>Practicall,</hi> which directeth the <hi>Will</hi> in its actions, in dictating unto it to doe good, and to flie evill: This is either <hi>Generall,</hi> as in generall to know that good ſhould be done; or <hi>Particular,</hi> as when it dictates that this good ſhould be done; and then either it is <hi>Practicall</hi> in <hi>part,</hi> or <hi>imperfect;</hi> or <hi>altogether, abſolutely,</hi> and <hi>perfectly;</hi> which, when the thing that is to be done being well exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined according to its ſubſtance and all its circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, it dictates, that it ſhould be done here, in this place, by me, in this time, notwithſtanding this oppoſition, &amp;c. and this ordinarily in the Schooles is called <hi>cognitio practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè practica,</hi> a <hi>knowledge practically practicall,</hi> i.e. altogether practical. Now I deſire to know of which of theſe ſeverall ſorts of light, or of <hi>knowledge of the Partie,</hi> this Doctor ſpeaketh, otherwiſe we cannot underſtand him?</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:111091:27"/>
            <p> In the 3. and 5. difficultie, we wiſh that our Brethren would declare unto us, whether by <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> they underſtand all thoſe who profeſſe, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitie in <hi>name,</hi> or thoſe only who profeſſe it <hi>really</hi> and in <hi>effect;</hi> and then; whether all thoſe who hold their <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalia</hi> or <hi>Eſſentialia</hi> only; or if they will them not to ſtand in meere <hi>fundamentall</hi> points, but alſo require that they paſſe unto their <hi>Superſtructories,</hi> and how farre? <hi>item,</hi> that they would diſtinguiſh between their <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtructory</hi> points in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and in <hi>manners;</hi> for this is the whole foundation and ground of this their debate: otherwiſe all that they ſay is but ſo many evaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and we cannot know wherein they diſſent from us, or what they would be at. <hi>Item,</hi> whether by the word <hi>[Church]</hi> they underſtand any <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>multitude</hi> that layes claime to this name? or the <hi>true Church?</hi> or the <hi>pure Church?</hi> and then whether <hi>pure</hi> in their <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia</hi> only, or alſo in their <hi>Superſtructories?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the 4. Difficulty: <hi>Common received practiſes in Chriſtianitie,</hi> are of as large an extent as Chriſtianity or the Chriſtian Church, and may ſignifie <hi>practiſes</hi> common to all Churches either <hi>nominally</hi> or <hi>really,</hi> or common to the only reall and true Chriſtian Churches, either in <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall</hi> points only, or alſo in <hi>Superſtructories,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all <hi>pure</hi> Churches only: The Doctor then, and his Sect, to the end they may be underſtood by us, whom they oppoſe, muſt clearely expound us what they meane by theſe words and expreſſions.</p>
            <p>But to cut off all ſort of Sophiſtication, and to bring them to the point, I will preſſe and urge them more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this faſhion: Either our Brethren in this point about <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> who are the <hi>adequate object</hi> of <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication,</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:111091:27"/>agree with us, or diſagree from us: if they grant the firſt, what needeth all this diſpute and contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones they fight but with their owne ſhadow, if the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, let them ſhew us wherein we diſagree; and either we ſhall give them ſufficient ſatisfaction, or render our ſelves to the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, in caſe we be gone aſtray from it.</p>
            <p>But to generalities we cannot anſwer. Neither is it Chriſtianly done by pretended Reformed and Reformers to caſt ſuch generall filthy aſperſions upon all the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, when as they can particularize nothing at all: The Lord lay it not unto their charge in that great day when all ſuch captions and ſophiſtications ſhall be in no requeſt.</p>
            <p>There be two maine objections, which ordinarily the Independents propound againſt the Government of all the Reformed Churches, and namely of that of <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Commiſſioners from <hi>pag.</hi> 2. §. 2. to the end of their Booke propound them in as great force as poſſibly they can have, and diſſolve them both ſo ſtrongly and evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is a wonder how this Well-willer had any ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach to reply. The Doctor alſo bringeth them from <hi>p.</hi> 14. §. 2. to the end of his booke, where he travaileth ſo ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, to juſtifie them, that he ſeemeth willingly deſirous to be condemned: onely rather then to be thought a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertor of the cauſe, he would rather anſwer impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then to quit his Brethren.</p>
            <p>The firſt argument put in forme, will be thus:</p>
            <p>Where there is or may be exhortation of partioular Churches one to another, and proteſtation of one againſt another and the withdrawing of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion one from another, (eſpecially when the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate interpoſeth his power) there the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritative
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:111091:28"/>power of Presbyteries and Synods is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>But in the Church of God or Militant Church, there is or may be exhortation of particular Churches, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> In the Church of God or Militant Church, the Authoritative power of Presbyteries and Synods is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The Aſſumption is certain.</p>
            <p>The proofe of the Connexion of the firſt Propoſition may be thus:</p>
            <p>Where there is a ſufficient remedy, and no leſſe effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall againſt all offences, then the Authoritative power of Presbyteries and Synods, or of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, there an authoritative power of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries and Synods, or of Excommunication is not neceſſary.</p>
            <p>But where there is, or may be Exhortation of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, &amp;c. there is a ſufficient remedy, and no leſſe effectuall againſt all offences then the Authoritative power of Presbyteries, Synods, or of Excommunication.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ergo,</hi> Where there is, or may be Exhortation of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, &amp;c. there is no need of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritative power of Presbyteries, Synods, or of Excommunication.</p>
            <p>They prove the Aſſumption here, for he who will or dare condemne the one, will not care for the other, unleſſe the Magiſtrates Authoritie intervene.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Commiſſioners anſwer 1. that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument ſuppoſeth an extraordinary Caſe, which hath ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fallen out in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111091:28"/>Churches, except thoſe of the Separation, who propound the Argument, viz. the pronouncing of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion or excommunication againſt a whole <hi>Church,</hi> and we hope ſuch a caſe never ſhall fall out. Now lawes are made for caſes that be ordinary, and not for theſe that are extraordinary.</p>
            <p>The Doctor replies, that they ſpeake not one word to extenuate the Authority of Synods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rep.</hi> But in depriving them of their Authoritative pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which is their <hi>forme,</hi> they extenuate their Authority yea they deſtroy their <hi>eſſence;</hi> for without an authoritative power, they ſit in quality of private perſons onely, or of Miniſters gathered together by chance, or otherwayes, and not in quality of Synods; or rather, as the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners anſwer moſt judiciouſly and clearely, In this <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> &amp;c. there is no more to be found then one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar member may do againſt another, which yet is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be inſufficient for removing of offences, unleſſe the Authority of the Church of which both of them are members, ſhall intervene.</p>
            <p>The Doctor replieth, that beſides <hi>Exhortations, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations, and non-communion,</hi> they profeſſo themſelves ever to ſubmit, and to have recourſe to the Civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Inſt.</hi> This <hi>profeſsion of ſubmiſsion</hi> is either <hi>voluntary,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending of their own free will; or by <hi>neceſsity</hi> of <hi>obligation,</hi> whereunto they are ſubject by <hi>Law:</hi> If they choſe the firſt, it is no more then a number of Watermen, Tinkers and Coblers may doe of them-ſelves by a particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. 2. It is not <hi>juris divini,</hi> as they pretend their Government to be, but <hi>humani,</hi> depending of their own fancy. And to profeſſe themſelves to be willing to have
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111091:29"/>recourſe to the civill Magiſtrate, it is not at all to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but moſt abſurd: 1. for that power of the Cl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Magiſtrate is not intrinſecall, but extrinſecall unto the Church: but we ſpeake only of the power that is intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall, and proper to the Church; and ſo muſt our Brethren alſo, if they will ſpeake rationally. 2. In ſo doing, they make the Civill Magiſtrate Judge of Eccleſiaſticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Doctrine and Diſcipline, and Head of the Church, &amp;c. which cannot hold when he is an Infidell, an Antichriſtian, &amp;c. whereof ſee more in the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners anſwer, and in the Obſervations and Annotations upon the Apologeticall Narration. 3. In ſo doing, ye make the <hi>Churcle power</hi> ſubordinate to <hi>Civill power,</hi> which cannot be, for ſubordination is betwixt things of the ſame kinde or ſort; but ſuch are not Civill and Eccleſiaſticall power, which are oppoſite, or rather contradiſtinguiſhed or differenced one from another, as things deſtinated to or different ends, the one ſpirituall, and the othertem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He complaineth that the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> call <hi>[them] theſe of the Separation,</hi> unleſſe withall they expreſt they meant <hi>the ſeperation from the</hi> Prolates wayes, <hi>as Scotland and England now doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, but they ſeparate themſelves alſo from the Sacramentall communion of all Chriſtian Churches, yea of all the Reformed Churches of the world: And (if it be true, what we have read in the letters from <hi>New-England</hi>) from the communion of one Church with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He ſaith, that <hi>ſuch a Caſe may fallout amongſt us, with ſwasmes of Anabaptiſts and Antinomians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That cannot be; for they have no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111091:29"/>with us, and therefore cannot be excommunicated by us. 2. It may eaſily fall out amongſt you, for the Anabaptiſts, as we have already ſhewed, are your owne, and not ours.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſayes, that the <hi>Commiſsioners</hi> ſuppoſe more in their ſecond Anſwer, viz. that two or more Churches <hi>may mutually preteſt and pronounce the ſentence of non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communion one againſt another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Doctor is either very dull, in not concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of this cleare and ſolid anſwer of the Commiſſioners; or elſe very malicious in diſguiſing of it; for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners argue here upon a Caſe, according to the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendenters Hypotheſis, which cannot but be ordinary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, according to their Diſcipline: and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit their Churches be very few, and have been a very ſhort time in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> yet it hath fallen out amongſt them in New England, and they have had the like Caſe in the Netherlands, according to their owne Relation: but in our way and Diſcipline it cannot fall out amongſt us; for if two Pariſh Churches have any difference, they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit themſelves both to the Colloque, or to the Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Aſſembly: if two Provinciall Synods or Aſſemblies differ, the Nationall Aſſembly judgeth betwixt them both; ſo that this Caſe cannot fall out amongſt us: and it is a practicall principle, that <hi>par in parem non habet im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium,</hi> ſince neither of the equals are ſubject one to the other; and ſuch are all Pariſh Churches amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Claſſes amongſt themſelves, and Provinciall Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Doctor by a Doctorall power jumpeth over the 3. and 4. Anſwer, with this worthy and moſt Laconicke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>viz.</hi> This <hi>ſame reply ſarveth to year third and fourth
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111091:30"/>anſwer.</hi> Which, whether it be truly ſaid, I remit it to the Readers judgement.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners fifth Anſwer is, <hi>By what probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity can it be made to appeare to any rationall man, and indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent minde,</hi> that <hi>no authority</hi> ſhall be as valid <hi>as authority</hi> againſt the obſtinate; that <hi>via admonitionis</hi> and <hi>requiſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> is equall with <hi>via citationis &amp; publiea authoritatis?</hi> There cannot bee ſo much as triall and examination of the offence without authority, unleſſe the party bee willing to appeare: that perſwaſion and juriſdiction, that the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering over to Satan, and thereby ſtriking the conſcience with the terrour of God by the authority of Jeſus Chriſt, which hath the promiſe of a ſpeciall and ſtrong ratificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in heavn, and any other Eccleſiaſticall way whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which muſt be inferiour unto this, and depend onely upon perſwaſion on the one part, and free will on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, can be ſuppoſed to be like efficacious. No man will ſay, but in civill matters it is one thing to have adoe with our neighbour, who hath no more authority over us, then we have over him; and another thing to have to doe with civill power, which hath authority over both: this ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I have written over in the Commiſſioners own words, becauſe it is ſo ſignificative, ſo ſtrong and evident, that it diſſolveth all the frivolous Replies of this good Doctor.</p>
            <p>The Doctor hence ſuppoſeth 1. That <hi>there is no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity but Scripture-authority,</hi> (by Scripture-authority I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve he meaneth that inſtituted by Scripture, otherwaies Scripture authority is the excellency of Scripture verity, which binds us to beleeve it, becauſe of its Author, which is God) 2. He ſuppoſes that to be moſt <hi>valid,</hi> that convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>and conquers actus elicitos,</hi> the <hi>minde,</hi> rather then <hi>that which doth onely manacle and conſtraine <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>us imperatos, the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111091:30"/>outward carriage:</hi> then makes his quaere thus, <hi>Is the way of admonition, proteſtation, and non-communion no authority?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Reply. But here the Doctor is mightily miſtaken, both in his <hi>Authority,</hi> and in his <hi>Actus eliciti,</hi> and <hi>Imperati.</hi> 1. For every thing that is ſaid in Scripture, howbeit its verity be grounded on Divine Authority, yet giveth it not men an authority or authoritative power; for what authoritative power is given to man or Angel by thoſe words, <hi>In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning God made the heaven and the earth?</hi> 2. Neither doth every <hi>admonition</hi> in Scripture made to men, arm them with authority, as that place of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> whereon the Doctor buildeth his authority, <hi>Give no offence:</hi> for it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth not an <hi>authority,</hi> or authoritative power to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, but an act of <hi>obedience</hi> to be practiſed. Item, no pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique power or authority, but a private duty, becauſe it is common to all men, which cannot be ſaid of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call authority.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe that other paſſage, <hi>better a milſtone were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged about ones necke, and he caſt into the Sea, then to offend a weake brother.</hi> Item, <hi>that we were better not to eate fleſh, then to offend, &amp;c.</hi> All this is ſaid by Divine Authority in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of its <hi>truth,</hi> in ſo farre as authority ſignifieth an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency or dignity in this truth, for which it ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, becauſe of the excellency of the Author, who is God, who cannot erre, by reaſon of the infallibity of his knowledge, or verity; or lead others into errour, becauſe of the goodneſſe of his will, or veracity: but to ſay that theſe paſſages ſignifie any authority, whereof wee ſpeake, <hi>i. e.</hi> either power to judge, to command, or to inflict ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall puniſhments, no reaſonable man can thinke it, that knoweth what power or authority meaneth. 1. For the acts of power are either imperative, or executive, or ſome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111091:31"/>other like, whereof none is here expreſſed. 2. Theſe <hi>ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> are all meerly <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ntiative,</hi> which <hi>formally</hi> are not <hi>authoritative,</hi> or of <hi>power.</hi> 3. <hi>Authority</hi> belongeth rather <hi>adfacultatem, actum, imperantem, quam ad elicientem;</hi> as this here. 4. The <hi>acts of power perſe,</hi> of themſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the <hi>will,</hi> and not to the <hi>underſtanding,</hi> as theſe here expreſſed. 5. They are not expreſſed by <hi>Verbes</hi> of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative</hi> or <hi>Optative,</hi> but of the <hi>Imperative mood;</hi> not in this faſhion, <hi>this ſhould be done; oh, that this were done;</hi> but in this; <hi>do this:</hi> whereunto ſometimes are annexed promiſes, in caſe of obedience; ſometimes comminations, in caſe of diſobedience; after which followeth the performance or execution, <hi>viz.</hi> actuall recompence, or puniſhment. 6. If an <hi>admonition,</hi> a <hi>proteſtation,</hi> or a <hi>non-communion</hi> be au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then every beggar hath this authority, yea as much as all the Churches of the world, as it followeth upon the Commiſſioners Argument, who ſay, that every neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour ſhould have it who hath no more authority over us, then we over them.</p>
            <p>The Doctor alſo is mightily miſtaken in limiting <hi>actus imperatos</hi> to the <hi>outward carriage;</hi> for many of the acts of the <hi>minde, will,</hi> and <hi>ſenſitive appetite,</hi> are <hi>imperati,</hi> as when I will underſtand, or willingly underſtand, when I will my ſelfe to will, and in vertue of that will I will. Item, when I will apply my appetite to good, and command it to doe good. No leſſe a fault is it in him to take <hi>actum elici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> in the ſame <hi>latitude</hi> with the <hi>actions</hi> of the <hi>minde,</hi> for ſome of them are meerly <hi>eliciti,</hi> &amp; others meerly <hi>imperati.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We grant you that to bee moſt valid that convinceth, and conquers <hi>actus elicitos, i. e.</hi> (as yee take it) the inward actions, rather then that which doth only <hi>manacle</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine actus imperatos,</hi> the outward carriage. But we deny
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111091:31"/>you that <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline,</hi> much leſſe your <hi>admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c.</hi> can doe it, for that is a work of Gods Almighty power only; hee onely who created all things, can create new hearts in us, and he onely who knoweth mens hearts can perſwade them: the voice of the Miniſter only ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth externally in our cares, but Gods Spirit to the heart. Neither is it the internall, or neereſt ayme of Diſcipline or Church Government to worke upon, or rule the mind, which is not knowne to the Church, or Church Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, but to procure the externall peace of the Church, which may be obtained, the minde remaining ſtill uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced. <hi>Aliud eſt, eſſe bonum Chriſtianum, aliud, bonum ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vem in Eccleſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Objection is, <hi>That by this authority and order of Government, one Church hath power over another, which is contrary to that liberty and equality Chriſt bath endowed his Church with, and is no other but a new Prelaticall dominion, ſet over the Churches of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners anſwer, denying that by their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment any particular Church can judge another; but that the whole Repreſentative Church in vertue of its ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregative power judgeth of them all, which they illuſtrate very prettily and judiciouſly by examples taken from the parts of a mans body, the Members of a Parliament, and Townes and Cities. Neither is it a Prelaticall dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as they calumniate it, for that of Prelates is extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call to particular Churches, as being incloſed in their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane Church, which is extrinſecall to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Churches, as not compounded of any of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <hi>per ſe,</hi> particularly called thereunto: but that of our Presbyteries and ſuch like Eccleſiaſticall Senates is intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall to every particular Church, being compounded of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111091:32"/>their <hi>organicall</hi> parts, or Miniſters, in vertue of their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall vocation, and particular miſſion, admiſſion, or electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on particularly called thereunto. But here I pray the Reader to conſider the Commiſſioners moſt cleare and judicious expreſſions, which being compared with this well-willers reply, will ſufficiently refute all he ſaith.</p>
            <p>Our Well-willer replieth: <hi>Sure your Lawes doe impoſe, that one Congregation ſhall be ſubject to the Elders (ſuppoſe) of twenty Congregations; And the Authority of nineteen of them is as Collaterall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Note here <hi>fallaciam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a captious Argument, whereby he proves one thing for another, that which is not in queſtion, for that which is in queſtion: viz. an Authority that is <hi>as collaterall,</hi> in ſtead of an Authority that is <hi>collaterall;</hi> which is an Epidemicall ſickneſſe in independent Divinity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwer, that the Elders of particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who ſit in Claſſes and Synods, may be conſidered two wayes: 1. <hi>Materially,</hi> as men, who are Elders: 2. <hi>Formally,</hi> in quality of Elders; and then againe, either 1. in quality of <hi>particular Elders,</hi> tied to ſuch a <hi>particular Church,</hi> in vertue of their particular <hi>Miſsion, Admiſsion,</hi> or <hi>Election,</hi> made by ſuch a particular Church; or 2. in quality of <hi>Elders in generall,</hi> called to feed the whole Church, in vertue of their <hi>generall vocation;</hi> which againe as the Author of the Obſervations and Annotations told you, may either be conſidered <hi>in actu ſignato,</hi> when only it is ſignified to belong to their Charge, before they exerciſe it, or in <hi>actu exercito,</hi> when in vertue of ſome <hi>Miſsion, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſson,</hi> and <hi>particular Commiſsion</hi> they may exerciſe it.</p>
            <p>If the <hi>Elders</hi> of <hi>particular Churches</hi> be conſidered <hi>mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially</hi> only, they are not ſo much as <hi>formally Elders:</hi> If 2.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111091:32"/>
               <hi>formally,</hi> in quality of particular Elders, tied to a <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church,</hi> they have not power to <hi>reed</hi> any Church but heir owne particular Church. And in this ſenſe it is an <hi>untruth,</hi> that any <hi>one Congregation is ſubject to nineteene or twenty particular Congregations.</hi> Yea, they are ſo far from this diſorder and confuſion, that the Paſtour of one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation cannot preach in another without the conſent of that particular Congregation, as the Rules and Lawes of our Eccleſiaſticall Diſcipline may <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, if they be conſidered. 3. In vertue of their <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ll <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ion</hi> they have power to <hi>rule</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> and may <hi>actually</hi> doe it in Synods, <hi>in acta ſignate,</hi> if they be conſidered pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely, before their particular miſſion and commiſſion, and <hi>in actu exercito, i.e</hi> they may exerciſe it actually after their <hi>particular commiſſion,</hi> their <hi>miſtion</hi> from their particular Repreſentative Church, and admiſſion into the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative or Collective Body or Aſſociation and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of many particular Churches, whether <hi>Claſicall</hi> or <hi>Synodall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter Well-willer replyes, that <hi>the Congregations eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one choſe their owne Officers to rule ever them in the Lord, but not to rule ever themſelves, and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. What is Well-willer underſtandeth by <hi>Congregations,</hi> whether Miniſters alone, of Ruling Elders alone, or both together, or men, or all men, women and children, and in a word, all the members of the Church, I know not. Neither doth hee expreſſe his minde upon this point. Only I muſt ſay, that being once in company with ſome of their Preachers; I heard ſome women maintaine ſtoutly in presence of the Miniſter, without any contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction made by him, that women alſo had power in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clefiaſticall Aſſemblies to judge of Controverſies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111091:33"/>and in matter of all Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I anſwer, it is one thing 1. to call a Church Officer to his charge, or to give him his vocation or calling: 2. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother to ſend him into the charge, or to give him his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: 3. another to admit him into the charge, and to elect him or chooſe him. The firſt is an act of the Church of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers who examine his life and Doctrine, and afterwards give him his Ordination, in the name of the whole Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. The ſecond is an act of thoſe who ſend him, and ſometimes is done by the Miniſters in a Colloque, or a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, which give him his Ordination; as when hee is ſent to feed a particular flocke; ſometimes by a particular Church, as in ſome particular Commiſſion to a Claſſe, or Synod, but in the name of the univerſall viſible Church, as yee ſee in the Aſſembly at Antiochia, in ſending ſome Miniſters to the Aſſembly at Hieruſalem. The third is an act ſometimes of particular Churches, as in the <hi>admiſsion and election of their owne Miniſters.</hi> Sometimes of a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loque and Synod, as in the <hi>admiſsion</hi> of the Members ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as in that Synod at Hieruſalem. And here to avoid all Sophiſtications of our Adverſaries, note that I ſpeak here only of the viſible Church according to its viſible forme, and conſequently of the viſible and externe Vocation, Miſſion, Admiſſion, and Election of Miniſters: ſo I ſay e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Church chooſes, <hi>i. e.</hi> elects its owne Miniſters, but it calleth them not, nor ſendeth them; It giveth them not their generall Vocation nor Miſſion into the Miniſtery, but that is an act of the whole Church, which <hi>in actu ſignato</hi> belongeth to the whole Church, but <hi>in actu exercito,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the exigence of time and places to particular Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, not in quality of Miniſters of particular Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but of greater conſociations, in a repreſentative bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111091:33"/>of many particular Churches. So a Miniſter in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod hath power of God by the whole viſible Church to judge, rule, and feed many Churches, <hi>poſitis ponendio, &amp; ut poni debent;</hi> ſo as nothing thereunto requiſite bee want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but all ordered as it ſhould, <hi>viz.</hi> if it be by conſent or election of his particular Church, and he bee admitted by the Claſſe or Synod whereunto he is ſent, &amp;c. as it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily practiſed in our Reformed Churches.</p>
            <p>Maſter Well-willer replyeth againe, <hi>That Epiſcopacy is as intrinſecall to particular Churches, as the Presbyteric, ſince Biſhops are choſen by the people at their inſtalment, where cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomarily people are allowed to make any juſt exception.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I deny the Aſſumption, <hi>viz.</hi> that it is as <hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall,</hi> and that for the reaſon brought by the <hi>Commiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> As for that which hee bringeth for confirmation thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they are choſen by the people, I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer 1. It is not enough they have their Election from the people, but they muſt alſo have their Vocation and Miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the Church in the name and authority of Chriſt, which they have not according to this Well-willers owne Tenets. 2. Becauſe the people can make no Church Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, and principally Miniſters, ſince they have not the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities to judge of their learning and gifts. 3. In chooſing of an Archbiſhop it is not morally poſſible that all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can elect him, and eſpecially when he is a great Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, or a Primate over a whole Kingdome, for all the people cannot well meet together. 4. And howbeit they could meet, yet could not their conſent and voyces eaſily be gathered. 5. It were a ridiculous thing in chooſing of him to ſeek the conſent and voyces of every idle and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant fellow, yea of women, that are of the people. 6. Neither is it enough to choſe a Biſhop, to make any juſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111091:34"/>exception, for that is not to elect him, but to hinder his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. 7. Neither is this ordinarily practiſed. 8. And Maſter Well-willer to the Biſhops here confeſſeth in the next line, that it hath had little ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>But Maſter Well-willer confirmeth it out of that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paſſage of <hi>Hieronymus, To avoid Schiſme one of the claſsicall Presbyterie was choſen to be as Chair man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Such a Biſhop is not an Engliſh, or Papiſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, but a Moderator of the action, or a Maſter of the Chaire, which will not make up a Biſhop, in ſo farre as a Biſhop is diſtinguiſhed from an ordinary Miniſter, for yee your ſelves pretend to have your Synods, which cannot be without ſome Moderator, Preſident, or Maſter of the Chaire, and yet ye deny that ye have any Biſhops, or Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopall Government. 2. Neither are Biſhops annually. 3. To bee ſhort, Maſter Well-willer bringeth us here no reall, but imaginary Biſhops, in the Kingdome of Utopia, <hi>viz.</hi> that are only Maſters of the Chaire, annuall, &amp;c. 4. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, <hi>whoſe Chancellour, Archdeacon, &amp;c. were Pariſhioners.</hi> 5. Their Chancellours are not ordinarily Eccleſiaſticall, but Lay-men, as ye call them, who nevertheleſſe judge of all Eccleſiaſticall Cauſes, which ye ordinarily blame. 6. Neither have they Vocation from God, as yee confeſſe. Neither are they choſen by all the Churches that they rule and feed, if any food they give, and feed not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the fat of the people.</p>
            <p>You are alſo too bold Maſter Well-willer, to ſay <hi>that the people formerly have beene as willing they ſhould reigne as ever any people were in your Kingdome to have the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ever them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We can ſhew you hundreds, yea thouſands, who have cutled their Government both in <hi>England</hi> and in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111091:34"/>
               <hi>Ireland;</hi> and what hath been the good will of the Scots towards them, they can beſt tell themſelves, as having felt it theſe foure or five yeares laſt paſt. But as for the Presbyterian Government, ye have never heard the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple murmure, much leſſe riſe up againſt it. 2. But if it be ſo, that ye have found them ſo ſweet, what needed ye run away, and deſert the Church here? They did compell Miniſters and Churchwardens to doe many things againſt their conſcience, and in caſe of refufall did ordinarily un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe them, as we can produce many examples both in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> yea of the Independenters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, before that they ſpake this way, in deſpite of the Reformed Churches. The like of this cannot without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular impudence be ſaid to have been any where practiſed by any Scots Presbyterie. We grant you, that it is not the <hi>peoples conſent only, but if according to the Word that makes a Government lawfull.</hi> But wherefore may not a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall repreſentative Church as well chooſe men for Claſſicall Aſſemblies, as for Synods? What pattern have you for the one rather then for the other? To all this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to your uſuall cuſtom, ye ſay much, but prove litle or nothing of what is in diſpute betwixt us: many books ye make, but little to the purpoſe: And now when ye can doe no better, ye can your ſelves moſt deſperately on the Biſhops ſide, to maintain their cauſe, when ye are yet too weake to maintaine your own.</p>
            <p>This Well-willer, in the end of his Booke, wiſhes that the Commiſſioners <hi>golden ſpeech be written upon all their actions, viz. That thoſe that are moſt averſe to Presbyterie, if they allow no matertall difference in Doctrine, Worſhip, or Practice, might enjoy their peace, and all comforts of their Miniſtery, and Profeſsion under it, without controllment of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111091:35"/>that Authoritative power which they ſo much apprehend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thereunto replieth, <hi>We have</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>been of late made to feare the contrary, by the reports of ſome (not of the meaneſt ranke) rf your own Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No godly man, that knoweth what is Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Government, can doubt of it; for according to the rules thereof, 1. no man is compelled to be Actor in any thing againſt his own conſcience. 2. If you will be under it, and allow no materiall difference, &amp;c. without doubt the Synod and all Orthodox Churches will cheriſh you, and aſſure you of it.</p>
            <p>But if ye wil ever live in Panick feares, and be ſo witty as evermore to find out new matter of jealouſies to vex your own ſoules, and make you to live in ſuch a perpetuall diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, all the forces of the King and his three Kingdomes is not able to hinder it; ye muſt truſt in God, and admit of ſuch ſecuritie from your Brethren as morally ye can have: If this doe not the buſineſſe, we know not what to adviſe you.</p>
            <p>As for that Anonymous Country-man of ours, who he can be, and if any ſuch be, and whether his diſcourſe with you could give you matter of juſt feare, we know not, and therefore forbeare to anſwer: Only I wiſh ſeriouſly on your behalfe, ye would doe nothing againſt the glory of your God, the weale of your Country, or to the breach of charity with your Brethren, who ſo much deſire to live in peace with you all. <hi>The peace of God be with you all.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:111091:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
